<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" []>
	<article>
	<articleinfo>
		<title>MMBase Internationalization and Localization</title>
		<date>2002-10-19</date>
		<edition>$Id: i18n.xml,v 1.9 2004-07-12 16:32:14 michiel Exp $</edition>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<firstname>Michiel</firstname>
				<surname>Meeuwissen</surname>
				<affiliation>
					<orgname>Publieke Omroep</orgname>
				</affiliation>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<legalnotice>
			<para>This software is OSI Certified Open Source Software. OSI Certified is a certification mark of the Open Source Initiative.</para>
			<para>The license (Mozilla version 1.0) can be read at the MMBase site. See <ulink url="http://www.mmbase.org/license">http://www.mmbase.org/license</ulink>
			</para>
		</legalnotice>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			Since MMBase is basically a server-product, there is only little user-interface, and the issue
			of which human language (or other `locale' setting) is in use is relatively unimportant. There
			can be said a few words about it though, and if you want to adapt MMBase to the needs of your
			country and language, then you can hopefully find what you need in this document.
		</para>
		<para>
			Happily MMBase is relatively well `internationalized', which means that effort has been taken
			to make it possible to `localize' (i.e. basically: add translations) it easily. MMBase was
			developed in a Dutch environment, rather then an English-only one, which ensured that this
			issue was always kept in mind relatively well.
		</para>
		<para>
			Part of the process of `internationalization' (also referred to as `i18n') of course is the
			possibility to represent all kind of characters, and on this subject the first section will
			elaborate.
		</para>
		<para>
			The second part of this document will point out where the different `translatable' parts of
			MMBase are, and how to add or improve a translation.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="encodings">
	 <title>Internationalization - Encodings</title>
		<para>
			In MMBase 1.5 and before the default character encoding of the strings in the database was
			ISO-8859-1, which is a superset of ASCII. In `iso-1' every letter is presented by exactly one
			byte, so that there can be only 255 different letters and characters. Using ISO-8859-1 most
			western European language - including English, French, German and Dutch - can be presented
			without much trouble.
		</para>
		<para>
			MMBase however is coded in Java, and Java strings can contain much more than 255 different
			characters. In fact the characters in Java strings must only be in the Unicode character set,
			which is a huge set, sufficient to present texts in virtually all languages of the world. See
			<ulink>http://www.unicode.org</ulink>.
		</para>
		<para>
			Therefore in MMBase 1.6 the encoding of the database strings was made configurable. Of course
			this is only needed if the database (and jdbc driver) does not understand unicode encodings by
			itself. E.g. mysql does not support unicode by itself, so MMBase has to force it.
		</para>
		<para>
			Default this 'encoding' parameter (which can be found in mmbaseroot.xml) is now set to UTF-8,
			which is the most common unicode encoding. UTF-8 is a multibyte encoding, which means that one
			character can be presented by 1 or more bytes. It has been arranged that the ASCII letters are
			presented by the same bytes, which means that texts encoded in ASCII are also encoded in
			UTF-8, so UTF-8 is largely backwards-compatible.
		</para>
		<para>
			Most configuration in MMBase is done by use of XML nowadays. Unicode characters can always be
			presented in XML documents by the use of `entities' or by the use of UTF-8 (the default
			character encoding for XML-documents, IIRC).
		</para>
		<para>
			Though Java strings can contain any unicode character, usually Java-code cannot be in
			e.g. UTF-8. I think java code must be in ISO-8859-1 (right?), so if a unicode character
			outside the range of ISO-8859-1 has to be presented in Java source code then it has to be
			escaped by the use of the \u notation.
		</para>
		<para>
			This also is valid for Java `property files'. Property files are not seldom used as resources
			for translations, so it is important to realize that they must be encoded in ISO-8859-1, but
			that it <emphasis>is</emphasis> possible to use characters from the complete unicode set. You
			might want to use a tool to do the escaping for you though if you try to type a language of
			which most characters are not in ISO-8859-1 (e.g. Greek, Russian and most Asian languages).
		</para>
    <section id="images">
      <title>Non-ascii in Images</title>
      <para>
        Usually the 'convert' tool of imagemagick is used to resize, turn or otherwise convert
        MMBase images. It is also possible in this way to add text to existing Images. 
      </para>
      <para>
        The java strings are then fed to the 'convert' tool by a runtime call. The convert-tool
        expects the string to be encoded according to UTF-8. It is not possible to tell this to
        Runtime.exec, neither is it clear how you should inform Java about this.
      </para>
      <para>
        The current implementation works, also for non-ascii characters, if the java environment is
        configured for UTF-8. In Linux this is the case if e.g. the LC_ALL environment variable is
        set to "en_US.UTF-8" or "nl_NL.UTF-8" or so.
      </para>
    </section>
	</section>
	<section id="translations">
		<title>Localization - Translations</title>
		<para>
			On a few parts in MMBase there can be found texts in different languages. A language is
			always indicated by a two letter code from ISO 639 (note that this is for languages, not
			countries).
		</para>
		<para>
			The internationalization of MMBase currently only extends to the real user interface
			parts, by which is meant in practice `content editors'. There does not yet exist an
			internationalized administration user interface. Another thing which one might
			imagine subject to internationalization are error messages, specifically those which
			can appear to users and templaters; all error messages from the MMCI and the MMBase
			Taglib can now only appear in English (or broken English). Some of these messages,
			like Security exceptions (`permission denied'), can occasionally appear to editor
			users.
		</para>
		<section id="builder">
			<title>Builders</title>
			<para>
				`Builders' or `Node-types' are defined by the use of XML-files in MMBase. The description
				of the builder, complete with `GUI' names is present in the XML file, together with the
				GUI-names of the fields of this builder. It is easy to add translations. Simply duplicate
				the tags you want to translate, change the 'xml:lang' attribute and provide the
				translation. A good start are the `core'-builders. The translated builder and field names
				will be available in generic editors and for example also in the editwizards.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="jspeditors">
			<title>Generic JSP-editors</title>
			<para>
				The generic JSP-editor does use some text of itself. These messages are internationalized
				and can be translated by adding a
				org.mmbase.applications.jsp.editors.editors_&lt;language&gt;.properties resource file
				containing the new translations.
			</para>
			<para>
				Translations for a few languages are available in the mmbase.jar but I think more can be
				put in the WEB-INF/classes/org/mmbase/applications/jsp/editors/ directory too (so there is
				no need to make a new mmbase jar). You can send the translations to the community though
				and then they can be placed in the mmbase jar for common usage.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="editwizards">
			<title>Editwizards</title>
			<para>
				Also the editwizards are relatively well internationalized. They output HTML-pages in
				UTF-8, so all characters can be present. Translations for the `current' language are
				present in a `prompts'.xsl. The default (English) one is next to the other editwizard
				XSL's, but it can be overridden by placing a translation in
				&lt;editwizard-dir&gt;/data/&lt;language&gt;/xsl/prompts.xsl. A few examples are shipped
				with the 1.6 MMBase distribution.
			</para>
			<para>
				In the editwizard `schema' XML's the prompt for a field can be explicitly stated. If you
				omit this prompt though the internationalized version of the builder is used in stead.
			</para>
			<para>
				The schema XML itself is also internationalized, and titles, prompts and other
				messages in these files can be present in more than one
				language. This is done by the 'xml:lang' attribute. There are
				bunch of `example' and `library' wizard xmls available in
				&lt;editwizard-dir&gt;data/samples and
				&lt;editwizard-dir&gt;data/lib, so for a nice and complete
				localization to your language, it would be nice to translate
				those too (search for the already present elements with an
				xml:lang attribute).
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section id="languagesetting">
		<title>Language setting</title>
		<para>
			In the mmbaseroot.xml also the `default language' can be set, which is used if no language
			is set.
		</para>
		<para>
			The language can also be set explicitly in the Cloud of the bridge (using the 'setLocale'
			function). GUI-names obtained from such a cloud will be localized according to this setting
			(if possible)
		</para>
		<para>
			The MMBase taglib provides the `locale' tag, which sets the language in cloud-tags in
			surrounds, but also informs other less MMBase specific tags (the time tag), about the locale
			settings it contains.
		</para>
	</section>
</article>
