<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <date>2002-06-27</date>
    <title>MMBase editwizard documentation</title>
  </bookinfo>
  <chapter id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>Several active users of MMBase have hired Q42 for developing the EditWizards upon MMBase.
EditWizards should allow the administrators to easily create wizard-like web-entry forms
for content entry and maintance.

The current release is 1.0. 

Administrators should clearly keep in mind that the EditWizards should be used for special content tasks only.
The wizards will not work well if you use them to edit all possible relations and fields of an object;
the wizard will be too complex and there will be no real advantage for using the wizards.
Example: create a wizard that allows editors to add a user to the system and place images and organisational information along with it.
Remember that a wizard with more than say 3 steps is over the top. Users will not like them.

In this document you will learn how to install the Editwizards on your MMBase release,
and you will learn how to create your own wizards.

First you will see what the basics are and how the most simple wizards should be set up.
Then, you'll see how more complex wizards can be created.
</para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="installation">
    <title>Installation</title>
    <para>If you install and run an 1.6 or higher release of MMBase, the editwizards will be installed also.
To let the editwizards run properly, the /mmapps/editwizard directory must be in place also.
This directory contains the JSP pages, the wizards, the images, XSL's and CSS and client-side Javascript code.
</para>
    <sect1 id="requirements">
      <title>Requirements and assumptions</title>
      <para>The editwizards can be used by the following browsers:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Internet Explorer 5.0 and higher on Windows platforms</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Internet Explorer 5.1 and higher on Apple Macintosh platforms</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Netscape 6.1 and higher on any platform</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Mozilla 0.9.6 and higher on any platform</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>And, you'll need a running instance of MMBase (as from version 1.6, the editwizards are included).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="assumptions">
      <title>Assumptions</title>
      <para>This assumes the right builders are available for the demo's. If not, make sure the right builders are active.  You can do this by deploying the 'MyNews' application (By the admin pages or by setting the status of the MyNews.xml to active)
The editwizards rely heavily on XML and XSL. Therefore, this guide assumes you know something about xml nodes and attributes and how to make valid xml documents.
</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="upandrunning">
      <title>Are the editwizards up and running?</title>
      <para>To make sure the wizards are up and running, you can try the following:<orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Make sure your mmbase and webserver is up and running</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Open a browser </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Type in the url to the editwizard, eg.: http://localhost:4242/mmapps/editwizard/</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>A simple html file should show with a few online demo's</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the link to "A very simple example (no taglib on entrance page)"
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the demo to "Images"
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>A login screen should popup. Login as you would with the MMEditors or the MMBase admin.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>If you logged in correctly, a list of images should be shown. 
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Let's try to upload a new image. Click on the right-bottom star-icon to upload a new image.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>A wizard-form should be shown. Enter a title of the image and its description. Click on 'Upload new Image'
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Brows to an image, select it and click on open.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>By clicking on "Save" you store the image in MMBase.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
</book>
