<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>MMBase Architectural Overview</title>

    <date>2003-03-20</date>

    <edition>$Id: architecture.xml,v 1.6 2003-08-20 20:19:38 henk Exp $</edition>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Henk</firstname>

        <surname>Hangyi</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>This software is OSI Certified Open Source Software. OSI Certified
      is a certification mark of the Open Source Initiative.</para>

      <para>The license (Mozilla version 1.0) can be read at the MMBase site.
      See <ulink url="http://www.mmbase.org/license">http://www.mmbase.org/license</ulink></para>
    </legalnotice>

    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.1</revnumber>

        <date>2003-03-20</date>

        <authorinitials>HH</authorinitials>
      </revision>

      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.2</revnumber>

        <date>2003-08-20</date>

        <authorinitials>HH</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>MMBase is a general purpose object oriented content management
    system, which is implemented in Java. MMBase operates as a web-application
    which can be plugged-in at an application server like Tomcat, Orion,
    Resin, WebSphere, Jetty or IIS.</para>

    <note>
      <para>The main difference between a webserver like Apache and an
      application server is that an application server is capable of executing
      server-side functionality like programs written in Java. The application
      servers on which MMBase can be plugged in have to support Java and Java
      Server Pages.</para>
    </note>

    <graphic fileref="media/architecture.png" />

    <para>This document provides an overview of the MMBase architecture. Each
    component in the architecture is described. Suggestions for further
    reading are given. The MMBase architecture can be subdivided into the
    following layers.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Database Access</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>MMBase Core</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Security</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Bridge</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Plugins</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Database Access</title>

    <para>MMBase is connected to a database via the JDBC interface. MMBase 1.6
    supports the following relational databases.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Informix</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>PostgreSQL</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>MySQL</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>HSQL</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Oracle</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DB2</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>A number of features of the MMBase Database layer are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Database transparency</para>

        <para>Ones you&#39;ve created a database and connected it to MMBase,
        MMBase will do the rest for you. It will take care of the creation of
        tables and will generate and take care of link tables. So the only SQL
        statements which you have to learn to being able to work with MMBase
        are: creating a database, making a backup of a database, restoring a
        database and dropping a database.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Automatic index generation</para>

        <para>When MMBase fills your database with tables it automatically
        creates indices for columns, which are known to be frequently used in
        database queries. This will guarantee that the database layer operates
        in an efficient way right from the start.i</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>[TO DO: what do we have to say about Query and Storage? ]</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>MMBase Core</title>

    <para>MMBase is an object oriented content management system. Content is
    stored in objects. Objects can be connected to other objects by relations.
    These relations are also objects, which can also contain content. Next to
    containing content, objects can also have functionality. E.g. the image
    object has the functionality to convert and scale images. The MMBase Core
    provides the mapping from the relational database layer to the object
    oriented layer. It is capable of:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>configuring objects and relations.</para>

        <para>MMBase objects are configured by XML-configuration files called
        builders. These builders describe the fields an object has and its
        functionality. The field names for use in the Graphical User
        Interfaces can be stored in multiple languages to make your MMBase
        implementation ready for use in different languages. After a builder
        is placed in the MMBase installation, the corresponding table in the
        database is automatically created. To learn more about using builders
        check out the Administrators/MMBase Builder Configuration
        documentation . In the MMBase standard builders document under the
        Templaters and Designers section you can find info on the builders
        shipped with the MMBase release.</para>

        <para>[TO DO: should both builder docs not be in the same section ? ]</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>creating objects and relations.</para>

        <para>When an object, or node, is created the functionality added to
        the object can dictate that some action has to be taken. E.g. an email
        which is stored in MMBase is posted.</para>

        <para>The creations of relations is a four-step procedure:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Create a builder with the fields that are necessary in the
            relation.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Add the relation to the list of relation definitions
            (RelDef)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Enter the source-relation-destination information into the
            list of relations types (TypeRel)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Create relations.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>See the document on relations in the Information Analysts
        section for more information on this topic.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>updating objects and relations.</para>

        <para>MMBase contains observers that listen to changes in objects and
        relations. When a change occurs, an observer can carry out some
        appropriate actions. Most observers are used to keep the MMBase caches
        up to date. Examples of such MMBase caches are the cache with
        converted images and the query cache.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>retrieving objects and relations.</para>

        <para>When retrieving information from the database, MMBase will store
        the results of the database queries for future use. This cache
        functionality helps to speed up performance. Next to caches for
        database queries, MMBase also contains a cache for storing converted
        images for future use. These caches are totally transparent.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>[TO DO: write document on Transactions and Multicast.]</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>MMBase offers an elaborated security layer for authorization and
    authentication. Authorization tells what a user is allowed to do.
    Authentication tells how a user can log on to an MMBase website. The
    security models available in MMBase 1.6 are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Cloud Security</para>

        <para>MMBaseusers are administrated in the MMBase object cloud. This
        security model offers a basic ranking system in Anonymous, Users and
        Admin.</para>

        <para>An advantage of the Cloud Security are that you can do your user
        administration via the webinterface and that you are able to integrate
        the MMBase users into your object model.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Context Security</para>

        <para>MMBase users are administrated in XML-configuration files on the
        file system. Users are part of Groups and Ranks. Each object in MMBase
        belongs to a context. The Context Security model offers an
        fine-grained mechanisms to specify rights of users and groups in
        different contexts. The model provides the possibility to define basic
        workflow schemes.</para>

        <para>The Context Security is especially fit if the rights of users
        has to be specified on object level or if you need basic workflow
        functionality. A drawback of the context security model is that the
        user administration can not be carried out via the web interface, but
        one has to use the XML-configuration files.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Context Cloud Security</para>

        <para>The Context Cloud Security provides the same functionality as
        the Context Security. In contrast to the Context Security, the Context
        Cloud security stores the authentication and authorization information
        in the object cloud.</para>

        <para>The Context Security is especially fit if the rights of users
        has to be specified on object level or if you need basic workflow
        functionality. A drawback of the context security model is that the
        user administration can not be carried out via the web interface, but
        one has to use the XML-configuration files.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Basic Security</para>

        <para>Provides the basic login functionality, where users are
        administrated in an file on the file system.</para>

        <para>This security model should only be used in combination with
        MMBase releases before version 1.5, that operate on basis of SHTML.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>No security</para>

        <para>Although trivial, it is sometimes handy to have an MMBase
        installation with no authentication, no authorization or no security
        at all. It won&#39;t come as a surprise that MMBase supports this
        functionality.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>To learn more about security see the The MMBase Security Framework,
    Installing and using Context Security, Installing and using Cloud Security
    in the Administrator section.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Bridge (or the MMBase Connection Interface)</title>

    <para>The MMBase Connection Interface handles the requests from the MMBase
    Plugins and passes them to the Security layer. See the Bridge (MMCI) API
    documentation under Templaters and Designers for more information on this
    topic.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Plugins</title>

    <para>There exist a growing list of plugins which add functionality to the
    MMBase Core. The most important plugins are listed below.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Taglib</para>

        <para>The taglib provides a set of tags which facilitate communication
        between MMBase and JSP-templates. See the MMBase taglib reference and
        the Creating webpages with the MMBase Tag Library in the Templaters
        and Designers section.</para>

        <para>One widely used tool build with the taglib are the JSP-editors
        for MMBase. With MMBase 1.6 to versions of the JSP-editors are
        included \mmeditors\jsp and \mmexamples\jsp\my_editors .</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Dove</para>

        <para>Dove facilitates communication between MMBase and XML-files. You
        can use Dove to build dynamic MMBase websites based on XML and XSLT.
        See the Dove XML API under the section developers to learn more about
        this topic.</para>

        <para>An important application that uses Dove are the MMBase
        editwizards. The editwizards let you create task-oriented
        user-friendly forms, which can be a big help for editors in working
        with MMBase. See the Editwizards documentation under the Templaters
        and Designers section for more information on creating and using
        editwizard forms.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>R-MMCI</para>

        <para>The Remote MMBase Cloud Interface makes it possible to
        communicate with different MMBase installation at the same time. This
        powerful plugin makes it possible to share and exchange data between
        MMBase installations irrespective of their location. See the Remote
        MMBase Cloud Interface under the section Developers to find out more.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>XML-importer</para>

        <para>The XML-importer can be used to import data from XML-files into
        MMBase. The XML-importer provides intelligent Find and Merge
        scenario&#39;s. More information can be found in the XML Importer (TCP
        2.0) documentation in the Developers section.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Applications</para>

        <para>The Applications plugin provide the functionality to package
        MMBase websites. See the MMBase Applications documentation under the
        Administrator section for more information on this item.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Editwizards</para>

        <para>The editwizards provide the functionality to define forms to
        edit the MMBase object cloud. Editors who do not frequently use MMBase
        might get lost in their MMBase object cloud, when using the default
        JSP editors to enter or change content, With the editwizards it is
        possible to build task oriented forms, which guide editors through
        their work. See the editwizard userguide and reference manual in the
        templaters section for more information on the editwizards.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</article>