<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Images and Attachments</title>
    <date>2005-05-09</date>
    <edition>$Id$</edition>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Michiel</firstname>
        <surname>Meeuwissen</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <legalnotice>
      <para>This software is OSI Certified Open Source Software. OSI Certified is a certification mark of the Open Source Initiative.</para>
      <para>The license (Mozilla version 1.0) can be read at the MMBase site. See <ulink url="http://www.mmbase.org/license">http://www.mmbase.org/license</ulink>
      </para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>
  <section id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      This document describes how you have to deal with images and attachments in MMBase. We will
      start with a simple description of what these things are for MMBase and how you can use them,
      and will end with some implementation details an MMBase developer might need to know.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="imageservlet">
    <title>Images and ImageServlet</title>
    <para>
      Lets start with the most simple thing, which is needed in almost every MMBase installation. Images
      are in MMBase just another form of content, so they can be stored in a builder (a.k.a. 'node
      manager'). This builder is named `images' in the MMBase distribution, and can be installed by
      deploying the resources' application. Normally the image itself will be stored as a blob in the
      database, though MMBase can be configured to do it differently. Of course normally the
      image-builder will also feature the meta information about the image.
    </para>
    <para>
      But there is more to it then this. There must e.g. be a way to present the image to the
      visitor of your web site. For the meta information about the image this is of course no
      problem, you can do that just as you would with other MMBase node fields. If you use the
      MMBase taglib you would for example list the related images like this:
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
<mm:relatednodes type="images">
   <img src="????" 
	height="<mm:field name="height" />" width="<mm:field name="width" />" 
	alt="<mm:field name="title" />" /><mm:field name="description" /><br />
</mm:relatednodes>
]]></programlisting>    
    </para>
    <para>
      As you know, you cannot use the image blob on you HTML page, but you need an URL which presents
      it. So that is why in the previous example I just typed '????'. Let's explain now how this
      issue is solved in MMBase, how MMBase can provide this '????'.
    </para>
    <para>
      The answer is that we have created a servlet for you to do this. This servlet takes a
      node-number as its argument. It can then retrieve the node from MMBase and searches for a
      field 'handle' in this node, and the content of this is used to response the
      http request. Other fields of the node, such as 'itype' and 'title' are used to decorate the
      http response with the right headers, such as the content-type (which for an image is
      something else then for an HTML-page) and the content-disposition header (to supply a nice
      suggestion for a file name).
    </para>
    <para>
      In 'web.xml' it is configured which URLs correspond to this servlet. The suggestion of the
      distro is '/img.db' which means that then the image of node 123 is available on the url:
      http://yourhost/context/img.db?123. I like to map the image servlet to "/images/*", and then
      the image 123 is available on http://yourhost/context/images/123, which I find to look a bit
      better. 'yourhost' is the name of your web server and 'context' is the application context you
      have started MMBase in (it can be empty, then MMBase is running in the 'root' context, but
      this is not generally true).
    </para>
    <para>
      Well, you know that you do not need to know explicitly the host name of your server when you
      make your html page, because you can refer to the image relatively in the 'img' tag. It is
      also not very convenient to use an url like &lt;img src="/context/images/123" /&gt; because
      'context' can change (you can move the page to another MMBase instance in another context),
      and even the 'images/' part can vary between MMBase installations, because it can be configured
      to which URL the image-servlet is mapped by the application server.
    </para>
    <para>
      That's why in MMBase there are functions to retrieve this information for you automatically.
      If you use the MMBase Taglib there is the 'image' tag for this:
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
<mm:relatednodes type="images">
   <img src="<mm:image />"
	height="<mm:field name="height" />" width="<mm:field name="width" />" 
	alt="<mm:field name="title" />" /><mm:field name="description" /><br />
</mm:relatednodes>
]]></programlisting>    
      So, this image tag finds out for you in which context your MMBase is running and to which URL's
      the servlet is mapped and it then produces the right URL.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you do not use the MMBase taglib, then the same thing can be done. Here is an example
      using the 'bridge'.
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
NodeListIterator i = node.getRelatedNodes("images").nodeListIterator();
while(i.hasNext()) {
  Node image = i.nextNode();
  out.println("<img src=\"" + image.getFunctionValue("servletpath", null) + image getNumber() + "\"
      alt=\"" + image.getStringValue("title") + "\"/>" + image.getStringValue("description") +
      "/><br />");
}
]]></programlisting>

      This does about the same as the above taglib example.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        The taglib example is really a bit more advanced. For example it tries to add user information to
        the URL if necessary, and it tries to put a file name in the URL if that is possible for the
        servlet (which helps some browsers). I advice to use the image-tag if you can.
      </para>
    </note>
    <section id="conversion">
      <title>Image conversion</title>
      <para>
        As mentioned, images can be converted to other images. This is a very useful feature, because you
        often need smaller versions of an image, or perhaps a version of the image which is re-styled in
        another way to fit in the look and feel of your web site. These things can be automated by MMBase
        to a large extend, which makes the life for content editors easier, because for images it
        suffices to provide one (high quality) image, and MMBase can handle the conversion of this image
        to versions needed on the web site.
      </para>
      <para>
        Converted images are stored in a special builder named 'icaches' (cached images), so they are
        much the same as the source images, the only difference being that they are automatically
        generated.
      </para>
      <para>
        So for the image servlet is does not make much difference if it has to serve a 'cached' image or
        an 'original' image. 
      </para>
      <note>
        <para>
          The image servlet does however find out if the request node is a cached image, because in that
          case it has to search the meta-information, which is needed to provide sensible http response
          headers, in the original image.
        </para>
      </note>
      <para>
        But how does MMBase decide which 'icache' nodes must be created, and how can you know which are
        available, and to which original image they belong?
      </para>
      <para>
        The answer is that there is a function in the images builder which accepts 'conversion commands',
        and returns the node number of the 'icache' node which is associated with this original image and
        those commands. If such a node cannot be found, it will be created.
      </para>
      <para>
        The 'conversion commands' are passed in a string referred to as 'template'. This string contains
        the commands separated by the + character. The syntax of the individual commands is very similar
        to the command line options of the 'convert' command of ImageMagick, because that program is
        commonly plugged in to perform the actual conversion. 
      </para>
      <para>
        A very simple example of such a conversion template is "geometry(100x200)", which is the command
        to resize the image to fit into a rectangle of 100 x 200 pixels. So, the number of the icache
        node which is a conversion by this template of the image presented by the Node 'image' can be
        requested from the bridge like this:
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
Node image;
...
List arguments = new ArrayList();
argument.add("geometry(100x200)");
int iCacheNodeNumber = image.getFunctionValue("cache", arguments).intValue();
]]></programlisting>
        Of course this node number can then be fed to the image servlet, on precisely the same way as
        you would do for a normal image.
      </para>
      <para>
        In the MMBase taglib this functionality is also present in the before-mentioned image tag, and
        can be triggered by using the 'template' attribute. Showing the '100x200' version of the related
        images therefore would look like this:
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
<mm:relatednodes type="images">
   <img src="<mm:image template="geometry(100x200)" />" alt="<mm:field name="title" />" /><mm:field name="description" /><br />
</mm:relatednodes>
]]></programlisting>    
      </para>
      <note>
        <para>
          MMBase provides an abbreviation for this vastly used command 'geometry' which is simply 's' (for
          size), so normally you would encounter:
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
   <img src="<mm:image template="s(100x200)" />" alt="<mm:field name="title" />" /><mm:field name="description" /><br />
]]></programlisting>
          Which is precisely the same, only shorter.
        </para>
      </note>
      <para>
        Lets give also an example of a template which consists of more than one command, e.g. a 'size'
        command plus a rotate command:
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
<mm:image template="s(100x200)+r(90)" />
]]></programlisting>
        The order of the commands can be significant, and you can supply the same
        command more then once.
      </para>
      <para>
        TODO: overview of MMBase specific commands. Fonts and Texts. JAI implementation. 
      </para>
      <para>
        We refer to the documentation of ImageMagick for a complete description of all commands. Also in
        the image tag entry of the MMBase taglib reference guide there are given some examples.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="height_and_width">
      <title>Image height and width</title>
      <para>
        Until now we've said nothing about the 'height' and 'width' of images. In HTML you actually
        need to specify those in the height and width attributes of the img tag. Since MMBase-1.8
        height and width are fields of the two image-builders (images and icaches). These fields are
        automaticly filled by MMBase, so you should never have to worry about it.
      </para>
      <para>
        The image-tag however, provided only the URL of a cached image. So in the previous chapter
        the issue was ignored. It would be fixed if you have somehow access to the actual 'icaches'
        node. This is this indeed possible (using a 'nodefunction' tag), but this is not very
        convenient and there for there are 2 alternatives in the mm:image tag.
      </para>
      <para>
        The first alternative is the 'mode' attribute on mm:image. When its value is 'attributes' it
        will not only produce the URL for the image, but it will produce the 3 relevant attributes
        for a XHTML img-tag. Like this:
	<programlisting><![CDATA[
<mm:relatednodes type="images">
   <img <mm:image mode="attributes" template="s(100)" />
	alt="<mm:field name="title" />" /><mm:field name="description" /><br />
</mm:relatednodes>
]]></programlisting>
  So then you don't have to specify the 'src' attribute itself either, because it is provided by the image-tag now.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can also specify 'img' as a value for the 'mode' of the image-tag, which will, of
        course, produce an entire img-tag. You would probably end up with something like:
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
<mm:relatednodes type="images">
   <mm:image mode="img" template="s(100)" /><mm:field name="description" /><br />
</mm:relatednodes>
]]></programlisting>
      </para>
      <para>
        The second alternative is that the mm:image tag produces a 'dimension' variable which can be
        accessed using JSP2's Expression Language. This variable is available in the body of the
        mm:image tag. The URL is available as ${_} (as with any 'Writer' tag). One could end up with something like:
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
<mm:relatednodes type="images" id="image" >
   <mm:image template="s(100)">
     <img src="${_}" width="${dimension.width}" height="${dimension.height}" title="${image.title}" alt="${image.title}"  /><mm:field name="description" /><br />
   </mm:image>
</mm:relatednodes>
]]></programlisting>
	
      </para>
      <para>
        In MMBase-1.8, the creating of the converted image is actually 'lazy', so the icaches object
        is created without the byte-array first, which will only be filled on actual request of the
        client. This however has little influence on the height and width of the icaches object,
        because those are 'predicted', and are therefore available immediately, also when the actual
        conversion has not yet taken place.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="attachments">
      <title>Attachments</title>
      <para>
        Other types of data blobs can of course, just as images, be stored in MMBase. We call them generally
        'attachments'. There is in fact no need to make any difference between images and attachments. The
        'attachments' builder from the MMBase distro does indeed share the 'handle' field with the 'images'
        builder, but it also has some other fields which are lacking in the default images builder (filename,
        size, mimetype). Because of these small differences there is variant for the image servlet, the
        attachments-servlet.
      </para>
      <para>
        It works exactly the same as for images. You could even use the image-tag to create urls to
        the attachment-servlet. That would be a bit silly though, so there is also an 'attachment'
        tag. It does exactly the same. As mentioned though, Images can be converted into other
        images (they can be resized, turned etc.). This is of course not valid for attachments, so
        the 'template' attribute cannot be used on the attachment tag.
      </para>
      <para>
        For every day usage you know enough now. The following sections will be more technical.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="xslt">
    <title>XSLT</title>
    <para>
      Sometimes you want to generate output using XSLT. This happens for example in the Editwizard
      implementation and you can also do it on a JSP page using the `mm:formatter' tag. Generally,
      as in these two examples, the source XML would describe the fields of the MMBase nodes only,
      like e.g. &lt;field name="number"&gt;123&lt;/field&gt;. So, the same problem as in JSP/taglib
      arises, namely, how to convert this to an actual URL for the image or the attachment? The
      mm:image tag is not available in XSL.
    </para>
    <para>
      One could start with simply creating URL's using the number. You only need to know what the
      URLs of the servlets are then. These could possibly be passed as a parameter into the XSL, or
      could simply be hard-coded in your custom XSL.
    </para>
    <para>
      The problem would then be solved at least for attachments. For images, the problem is again
      more complex, because generally you would not include also the 'icaches' node in the XML.
    </para>
    <para>
      The solution which was used in Editwizards and also in the default XSLTs used by mm:formatter
      is to use Xalan extensions, which actually boils down to the possibility to call java
      functions from inside XSL. The draw-back of course is that this creates a Xalan dependency (or
      at least on similar products, e.g. also the XSLT processor of Resin supports this), and worse,
      that it would become quite hard to perform the XSLT not on the server itself.
    </para>
    <para>
      For this to work the utility class org.mmbase.bridge.util.xml.NodeFunction was created, which
      can be installed in your XSL like this:
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
<xsl:stylesheet  
    xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform"
    xmlns:node="org.mmbase.bridge.util.xml.NodeFunction"
    ....
]]>
      </programlisting>
      and then be used like this:
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
<img src ="{node:function($cloud, ./o:field[@name='number'], 'servletpath(,cache(s(100x100&gt;)))')}" 
      ]]>
      </programlisting>

      We refer to the javadoc  of       
      <ulink url="http://www.mmbase.org/api/org/mmbase/bridge/util/xml/NodeFunction.html">NodeFunction</ulink>
      for more information on how to use it.      
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="builders">
    <title>More about the builders, 'servlet builders'.</title>
    <para>
      It has become clear that the images and attachments builders are more than simple dumb MMBase
      builders ('Dummy). They do provide extra functionality like 'servletpath' and 'cache' functions.
      In the builder xml of Images and Attachments you can see this because another class is configured
      (by the 'class' tag (or 'classfile' in older XML's))
    </para>
    <para>
      The general feature of images and attachments nodes is that they need to be associated with a
      Servlet. Therefore the abstract builder 'ServletBuilder' was introduced which provides the
      general functionality for these kind of things. It provides the mechanism to determine the right
      URL to the right Servlet for a certain 'function' (ImageServlet provides the function 'images',
      AttachmentServlet provided 'attachments').
    </para>
    <para>
      The images, icaches and attachments servlets are all extensions of this abstract servlet
      builder. I suggest that if you need to create a builder which is associated to a servlet too, you
      do it like this.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="servlets">
    <title>More about the implementation of the servlets.</title>
    <section id="servdb">
      <title>Introduction, servdb</title>
      <para>
        Before MMBase 1.6 the function of the Image Servlet was performed by the generic MMBase
        servlet 'servdb'. 'Servdb' also accepts the 'template' as an argument next to the original image
        node number. In that way it could serve a converted image. An URL to servdb could therefore
        look like:
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
          <img src="/img.db?123+s(100x200)" />
          ]]></programlisting>
        This works fine, but it has a few disadvantages. First of all in this way you actually had to
        consider the 'context' yourself. In the above example it was supposed to be root, but it gets
        uglier if you want to let it work more generally.  Furthermore it was mandatory to map the
        servlet to 'img.db' (not a major problem, but it's a pity). It was also possible by doing
        requests on this servlet to use up a lot of resources on the server (anyone could trigger any
        conversion). 'servdb' did also not consider the MMBase security mechanism (which was created
        later), so it was not possible to protect the read rights of images. Using servdb, every image
        can be viewed by everyone who can do requests on it.
      </para>
      <para>
        All this lead to the new 'image servlet' implementation, which together with the 'servlet
        builders' (and 'image tag'), solves all of these problems.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="bridgeservlets">
      <title>Bridge servlet, handle servlet, image servlet</title>
      <para>
        Protecting read rights has nothing do with images. When you want to honor MMBase security, the
        only thing you have to do is implement your stuff using the bridge. Therefore the
        'BridgeServlet' was created. It provides the functionality to get the Cloud (perhaps using the
        session, if needed). It can be used to implement any MMBase servlet which actually serves
        data from the MMBase database.
      </para>
      <para>
        As mentioned before Image servlet performs some tasks to recognize a node
        as an icache node, and knows about the specific fields of an image-node. Attachments are about
        the same, but they do not need the icache recognition and do have some other fields. They both
        do share the functionality of searching an 'handle' field and responding its bytes. Therefore
        the 'HandleServlet' base class was created, which extends from BridgeServlet and which is
        extended by ImageServlet and AttachmentServlet.
      </para>
      <para>
        Since MMBase 1.8, the Image servlet also triggers the icache conversion if it detects that
        the 'handle' field of the requests icaches object is still unfilled. For that, the format of
        the 'ckey' field was changed a bit, so that it is possible now to use it to initiate the
        conversion.
      </para>
      <para>
        This means that a request on the image-server will block until the image-conversion is
        ready. In stead of the page on which appeares the URL to the image-server, as happened in
        earlier MMBase versions.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="configuration">
      <title>Configuration</title>
      <para>
        The following configurations are possible.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
