<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd"
[]>
  <article id="general_documentation">
	 <articleinfo>
		<title>About MMBase Documentation</title>
		<date>2002-12-05</date>
		<edition>$Id$</edition>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<firstname>Michiel</firstname>
				<surname>Meeuwissen</surname>
				<affiliation>
					<orgname>Publieke Omroep</orgname>
				</affiliation>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<legalnotice>
			<para>This software is OSI Certified Open Source Software. OSI Certified is a certification mark of the Open Source Initiative.</para>
			<para>The license (Mozilla version 1.0) can be read at the MMBase site. See <ulink url="http://www.mmbase.org/license">http://www.mmbase.org/license</ulink>
			</para>
		</legalnotice>
	</articleinfo>
	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			This document will describe in what way MMBase is documented, and how you can contribute to
			updating or adding to the MMBase documentation. But first have a look at the overview of available MMBase documentation and how it is organized. The documentation is mainly written for different target groups. Documents of one target group may be important for other target groups as well. For instance, backend and frontend developers will have also have to be familiar with the documents on builders and applications.
		</para>
		<graphic fileref="general/media/documentation.png"></graphic>
		<para>
			There are several sources of documentation and information available. First there is the MMBase website (www.mmbase.org),
			which does supply knowledge and examples. The examples and HTML documentation which are shipped
			with an MMBase distro are available in the MMBase CVS source repository. The examples pages
			are in the html/mmexamples module, so new examples must be added there.
		</para>
		<para>
			Formal documentation is available in the `docbook' XML format in the `documentation' modules of
			the CVS repository.
		</para>
		<para>
			Some older documentation, which was not yet converted or rewritten to the docbook format is
			available in html/mmdocs of CVS.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="docbook">
	 <title>Docbook</title>
		<para>
			Documentation is set up in articles. An article needs an articleinfo object that describes the content.
			Article info should contain :
	<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
						A title.  you do not need to specify the title in article if you
						specify it in articleinfo. (it's not wrong but it's not
						needed either)
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>A date. The International Standard ISO 8601 specifies numeric representations of date and times is used.
						So a date is written as 2003-07-28.If only the month or even only the year is of interest: 2003-02 or 2003.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						An edition tag with a  $Id$ content, for versioning of
						the data.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						An author group, with the authors. You can add an affiliation
						(organization) and your own name. Please do not add editors, links, or
						other stuff, as it will all be displayed in the documentation header and
						that may be a bit overkill (maybe we have to override the
						docbook xsl).
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						the following legalnotice:
						<programlisting>
					<![CDATA[
<legalnotice>
	<para>
		This software is OSI Certified Open Source Software. OSI
		Certified is a certification mark of the Open Source Initiative.
	</para>
	<para>
		The license (Mozilla version 1.0) can be read at the MMBase
		site. See
		<ulink url="http://www.mmbase.org/license">http://www.mmbase.org/license</ulink>
	</para>
</legalnotice>
]]>
						</programlisting>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			Use section, do not use sect1, sect2...
			And, if possible, use CDATA sections in your &lt;programlisting&gt;. This
			makes it easier to read when editing. CDATA sections look like this:
		 <programlisting>
&lt;programlisting format="linespecific"&gt;&lt;![CDATA[

	&lt;sample code&gt;

]]&gt;&lt;/programlisting&gt;
			</programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>Although it is only a minor issue: the documentation preferably is written in U.S. English.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="docbookeditors">
		<title>Docbook editors</title>
		<para>Several docbook-editors are available. A number of editors used by the MMbase documentation team:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Jedit</para>
				<para>Jedit is a Java-based text editor that uses colorcoding to ease editing of source code, such as java code, xml/html, and css. It provides a number of useful macros and plugins, including xml validation, tag completion, and xml auto-formatting.</para>
				<para>Has some issues: it is a bit slow and occasionally freezes up, but it provides auto-save facilities and can recover after a crash. A good color-coded editor that works on all java-supporting platforms</para>
				<para>see: <ulink url="http://www.jedit.org">http://www.jedit.org</ulink></para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Emacs</para>
				<para>
          A multi-platform open-source editor that provides several
          handholds for editing. It has an XML-mode with
          tag- and attribute completion, which makes creating valid
          Docbook documents easy.
        </para>
        <para>see: <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/">http://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/</ulink></para>
        <para>see: <ulink url="http://www.xemacs.org/">http://www.xemacs.org/</ulink></para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>XXE</para>
				<para>A Java tool that allows you to edit xml files (only), specifically docbook xmls. It provides ways to associate a stylesheet with a xml so it can render a pleasing presentation of the docbook while you edit it.</para>
				<para>With version 2.2 XXE solved the problems with handling or allowing edit of CDATA sections. XXE 2.2 generates nice formatted xml, which makes the results easy to read in other editors. XXE is able to convert XML files to html, RTF, Postcript and PDF.
				For non/semi-technical users XXE is found to be a very good choice to edit docbook documents!</para>
				<para>see: <ulink url="http://www.xmlmind.com/xmleditor/">http://www.xmlmind.com/xmleditor/</ulink></para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
</article>
