<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
    <articleinfo>
        <title>MMC Mission Statement Document</title>
        <date>2003-06-26</date>
        <edition>$Id: mmcmissionstatement.xml,v 1.2 2003-07-27 17:47:54 henk Exp $</edition>
        <authorgroup>
            <author>
                <firstname>Rob</firstname>
                <surname>Vermeulen</surname>
            </author>
        </authorgroup>
        <legalnotice>
            <para>This software is OSI Certified Open Source Software. OSI Certified is a certification mark of the Open Source Initiative.</para>
            <para>The license (Mozilla version 1.0) can be read at the MMBase site. See <ulink url="http://www.mmbase.org/license">http://www.mmbase.org/license</ulink>
            </para>
        </legalnotice>
        <revhistory>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>1</revnumber>
                <date>2003-06-26</date>
            </revision>
        </revhistory>
    </articleinfo>
    <section>
        <title>MMC Mission Statement Document</title>

        <formalpara>
            <title>Mission statement of the MMC (MMBase Management Committee)</title>
        </formalpara>

        <para>
            <emphasis>Maintain a stable platform for MMBase developers, and ensure a good evolution of the MMBase software. This includes, defining clear goals for the developers, and finding answers on questions and problems within the developers community.</emphasis>
        </para>


        <para>The MMC achieves its goal by fulfilling the following tasks:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Vision: Ensure that the developers have the same goals in mind.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Inform developers: Make sure the developer community is well informed.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Spokesman: Provide information about the developer community, and the MMBase software.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Clear information: Describe known problems/wishes and how they are being handled (or not).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Monitoring  projects:  Before  starting  projects  see if they are in line with the vision and if there are enough resources to execute the project, guarding progress of projects, monitor good termination of projects.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Monitoring source code: Ensure the source code is in line with the vision, and that all adjustments are reviewed.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Monitoring  distributions:  Ensure distributions are made within a regular interval. A release plan should be available always. Ensure that there are enough resources to make the distribution.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Monitoring resources: Maintain tools and hardware needed for the developers community.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Documents: Rules, regulations, licenses all should be defined good in proper documents.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Open source: Inform the open source community with our experiences.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>MMChat: Weekly meeting of MMC members.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Foundation: Support and communication with the MMBase foundation.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Flourish: Ensure developers meetings are arranged, ensure quality, ensure stability, ensure growth of community.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>
             Short term focus (6 months)
             </title>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Tools to administrate MMBase</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Separate core and applications</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Performance</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Stability</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Focus on current projects, such as: storage, search query, documentation, and media.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Developers portal</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>
        Long term focus (2 years)
        </title>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Mechanism to maintain MMBase applications (apps2)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Developers portal</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Documentation</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
</article>
