<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd">
<article class="specification" id="administrators_tune-production">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>How to tune MMBase for production</title>

    <date>2005-12-09</date>

    <edition>$Id$</edition>

    <authorgroup>
      <!-- one or more authors -->

      <author>
        <firstname>Nico Klasens</firstname>

        <surname></surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>[1.0]</revnumber>

        <date>[2005-12-09 ]</date>

        <authorinitials>[NK]</authorinitials>

        <revremark>First version</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>

    <abstract>
      <para>How to for fine tuning MMBase</para>
    </abstract>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>This software is OSI Certified Open Source Software. OSI Certified
      is a certification mark of the Open Source Initiative.</para>

      <para>The license (Mozilla version 1.0) can be read at the MMBase site.
      See <ulink
      url="http://www.mmbase.org/license">http://www.mmbase.org/license</ulink></para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <section id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Like every application, MMBase is not optimized for every production
    environment. Out of the box it is suitable for small sites with low
    traffic. This document will describe how to change the configuration of
    MMBase and what other things are involved to boost performance of a
    site.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="scope">
    <title>Scope</title>

    <para>The experience of an user that a site is slow is usually not only
    the fault of a web application. The request from a browser passes many
    systems before the response is returned. Every passed system will add a
    delay to the response. The web application is just a part of the cycle.
    This document describes how to tune MMBase, but it is only worth the
    effort when MMBase is the problem.</para>

    <para>Several systems in a production environment which can affect
    performance are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Internet connection to Internet Service Provider</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>FIrewalls which block and filter traffic</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Network with physical data limits and routing</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Webserver or proxy (e.g. Apache http server or IIS)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Operating system (I/O and network settings)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Other running applications on the system</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Database server</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Database settings</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Java Virtual Machine settings</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section id="bottlenecks">
    <title>Identify bottlenecks</title>

    <para>The first step, in identifying which systems perform poorly, is to
    divide the production environment in segments. Every segment represent a
    part of the response time.</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Browser - webserver</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Webserver and application server</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Database server</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Every system on a segment boundary should log the response time of
    the request to find the segment with the highest delay</para>

    <para>Browser</para>

    <para>Logging of the response time on the client can be done with several
    load test tools. A freely available one is Jmeter <ulink
    url="http://jakarta.apache.org/jmeter">http://jakarta.apache.org/jmeter</ulink></para>

    <para>Webserver or application server</para>

    <para>All frequently used servers can log in the access.log response time
    information.</para>

    <para>The apache http server uses the mod_log_config module which support
    custom log formats. See <ulink
    url="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.0/mod/mod_log_config.html">
    http://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.0/mod/mod_log_config.html</ulink> for more
    information on LogFormat and CUstomLog</para>

    <para>Apache Tomcat uses an Access Log Valve create a similar logfile as
    the apache http server does. For more information see <ulink
    url="http://tomcat.apache.org/tomcat-5.5-doc/config/valve.html">
    http://tomcat.apache.org/tomcat-5.5-doc/config/valve.html</ulink></para>

    <para>Database server</para>

    <para>Most databases can monitor the time a query requires to execute.
    This is different for every database and difficult to map to a request of
    one user. MMBase can also log the query response time by enabling the
    debug level on the Sqlhandlers. The log configuration is default in the
    log4j.xml in the mmbase.jar or /WEB-INF/config/log/ directory.</para>

    <para><programlisting format="linespecific">&lt;logger name="org.mmbase.storage.implementation.database.DatabaseStorageManager"
        additivity="false"&gt; &lt;level class="&amp;mmlevel;" value ="debug" /&gt;
  &lt;appender-ref ref="sqllog" /&gt;
&lt;/logger&gt;
</programlisting></para>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section id="browsersegment">
    <title>Browser segment</title>

    <para>If the response time is not acceptable is this segment then the
    problem is somewhere in:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Internet connection to Internet Service Provider</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>FIrewalls which block and filter traffic</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Network with physical data limits and routing</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>How to fine tune this segment is out of the scope of this
    document.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="databassegment">
    <title>Database segment</title>

    <para>The most common error in the database segment is that the indexes on
    the database are not present. indexes on the following columns should
    always be present</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>_object - number</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>_insrel - snumber</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>_insrel - dnumber</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>_insrel - rnumber</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>_typerel - snumber</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>_typerel - dnumber</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>_typerel - rnumber</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>_versions - name</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>_oalias - name</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>_syncnodes - exportsource</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>_syncnodes - exportnumber</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Other tables could also benefit from indexes. Mysql requires indexes
    on all snumber, dnumber and rnumber columns in tables containing
    relations. This is also the case for Postgresql. Postgresql extends the
    tables, but does not inherit the indexes of the parent table.</para>

    <para>Every web application build on top of MMBase has it own required
    indexes to perform well. The sql statements log as shown above will help
    identify which columns need an index. All columns mentioned in WHERE parts
    of the query are candidates for an index.</para>

    <para>See the documentation of your database how to do maintenance. A
    database can easily become a bottleneck over time.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="appserversegment">
    <title>Application server segment</title>

    <para>If the response time in this segment is very bad then the problem
    can be in several parts:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Operating system (I/O and network settings)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Other running applications on the system</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Java Virtual Machine settings</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>JSP code</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Custom application code</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>MMBase code</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The first thing to check is which resources on the server are
    overloaded and which processes are causing it: Monitor the cpu load,
    virtual memory usage and I/O operations statistics. When the cpu load or
    memory usage is not caused by the application server process then the
    problem is somewhere in other applications or the OS.</para>

    <section id="os">
      <title>Operating system and applications</title>

      <para>The first thing to check is that the last update release of the
      jvm is used. Every major release (e.g. J2SE 1.3.1, J2SE 1.4.2, J2SE 5.0)
      has update releases on a regular basis Update releases often include bug
      fixes and performance improvements. By deploying the most recent update
      release you will benefit from the latest and greatest performance
      improvements.</para>

      <para>The second thing to check is that all required software patched
      for the OS and jvm are installed. In the case of Solaris there is a set
      of patches that are recommended when deploying Java applications. To get
      these Solaris patches for Java please see the links under the section
      Solaris OS Patches on the Java™ download page. Solaris with not all
      patches installed can have high cpu loads. The cpu load is than
      generated by system libraries and not user code.</para>

      <para>Be aware that various system activities and the operations of
      other applications running on your system can introduce significant
      variance into the measurements of any application's performance,
      including Java applications. The activities of the OS and other
      applications may introduce resource CPU, Memory, disk or network
      resource contention that may interfere with your measurements.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="jvm">
      <title>Java Virtual Machine</title>

      <para>Before going into the details of the JVM realize that one of the
      advantages of Java is that it dynamically optimizes for data at runtime.
      A Java™ HotSpot™ virtual machine adapts and reacts to the specific
      machine and specific application it is running. In more and more cases
      Java performance meets or exceeds the performance of similar statically
      compiled programs. However this adaptability of the JVM makes it hard to
      measure small snippets of Java functionality.</para>

      <para>One of the reasons that it's challenging to measure Java
      performance is that it changes over time. At startup, the JVM typically
      spends some time "warming up". Depending on the JVM implementation, it
      may spend some time in interpreted mode while it is profiled to find the
      'hot' methods. When a method gets sufficiently hot, it may be compiled
      and optimized into native code.</para>

      <para>Before you start to tune the command line arguments for Java be
      aware that Sun's HotSpot™ Java Virtual Machine has incorporated
      technology to begin to tune itself. This smart tuning is referred to as
      Ergonomics. Most computers that have at least 2 CPU's and at least 2 GB
      of physical memory are considered server-class machines which means that
      by default the settings are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The -server compiler</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The -XX:+UseParallelGC parallel (throughput) garbage
          collector</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The -Xms initial heap size is 1/64th of the machine's physical
          memory</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The -Xmx maximum heap size is 1/4th of the machine's physical
          memory (up to 1 GB max).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Please note that 32-bit Windows systems all use the -client
      compiler by default and 64-bit Windows systems which meet the criteria
      above will be treated as server-class machines.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="memory">
      <title>Memory</title>

      <para>Even though Ergonomics significantly improves the "out of the box"
      experience for many applications, optimal tuning often requires more
      attention to the sizing of the Java memory regions.</para>

      <para>A lot of java developers don't know how memory management happens
      in the JVM. As a developer you don't have to care about memory
      (de)allocation. When an application is put in production it can be very
      important how the memory management system is tweaked. A badly tweaked
      application could halt for more then 10 minutes. This has been seen on a
      machine which had to swap a lot and had 1G assigned as max size (-Xmx).
      After tuning the settings it was reduced to 30 seconds or less.</para>

      <para>Garbage collection (GC) is one of the hardest things to do
      efficiently for jvm's. You can make some parameters explicit to the jvm
      which makes it much easier for the jvm to guess when it should do
      something.</para>

      <para>Most people know the parameters -Xms and -Xmx, but not what they
      will do to memory management and gc.A lot of MMBase instance in
      production do not have these settings or they are very high. In the 1G
      example the settings were reduced to 700M and it is still to high. The
      -Xms and -Xmx are allocating OS memory for the process. This is called
      the memory heap. When the heap is filled for 60% or more then the jvm
      will start a GC which will halt the process until it is finished (the 10
      minute break). The default heap setting is 64M which MMBase will fill in
      seconds with an average web application. The GC will run very frequently
      to free memory which means less application cpu time. Most MMBase
      applications require about 300M of heap size.</para>

      <para>Note that the -Xms and -Xmx settings does not match with what the
      OS returns for the memory usage of the process. The memory usage also
      includes program code and jvm code (j2se uses the jvm code in memory for
      all java processes). The memory footprint for the process have to stay
      below the physical memory to prevent high GC times. Setting the -Xmx the
      same as the physical memory will decrease performance, because it will
      likely result in paging of virtual memory to disk.</para>

      <para>In the next part where the jvm or java is mentioned the Sun jvm is
      meant. A lot is the same for others, but not everything. The Sun jvm is
      divided into several spaces. It has one permanent generation, one old
      generation and one new generation. The new generation is divided in an
      eden and 2 survivor spaces.</para>

      <para>The permanent generation is for storing the class objects and some
      other permanent stuff. In JSP environments when a lot of classes are
      loaded, it is a good practice to set the 'PermSize' value high enough.
      Full GCs are needed to extend the permanent generation.</para>

      <para>New object instances are created in eden (new generation). When
      eden is full then a small GC is performed to clean it. The instances
      still in use are copied to one of the survivor spaces and the rest will
      be cleared. When instances are copied multiple times to the survivor
      spaces then it will be promoted to the old generation. When the old
      generation is full then a Full GC will be preformed on the heap. A Full
      GC, in the default case, will mean a halt on the jvm. The new generation
      GC won't halt the jvm. The new generation GC is also much faster then
      the old generation GC.</para>

      <para>The ratio of the size of the generations based on the full heap
      size can have great impact on the throughput and halt time of the jvm
      especially when editwizards are involved. When you have memory issues
      then give it a shot with these settings</para>

      <para><programlisting format="linespecific">-server -XX:NewRatio=2 -XX:SurvivorRatio=6</programlisting></para>

      <para>The jvm has to run in server mode and not client mode. In client
      mode the ratio between old and new is -XX:NewRatio=8. This means that
      the new generation in client mode will be 1/8 of the heap and the old
      generation 7/8. In server mode the ratio is -XX:NewRatio=2. The new
      generation will then be 1/3 of the heap. The -XX:NewRatio=2 above just
      makes it explicit. The advantages are that more new instance can be
      created and die before a small GC is preformed.</para>

      <para>The -XX:SurvivorRatio is default 25. The reason to increase the
      Survivor spaces is to prevent that there are too many new instances for
      the survivor space. If it doesn't fit then the rest will go to the old
      generation right away. This will happen when the editwizards are
      installed. A user keeps a stack of wizards with a lot of instances on
      the server. A very big wizard can occupy 4MB of memory. All instances
      die when the wizard is closed. You want to keep these objects in the new
      generation. With a default server mode jvm with 1G the Survivor spaces
      are 12M. If you have multiple editors then the stacks with wizards can
      easily be more then 12M and instances will go to the old generation with
      a small GC and can only be cleared with a Full GC.</para>

      <para>To emphasize, in an ideal run you want your survivor space to have
      objects of different ages. That means you have enough space there to not
      instantly promote live objects to the old generation. This means less
      pollution of the old generation.</para>

      <para><programlisting format="linespecific">Default setup with 1G
Old generation 682mb (client mode: 910)
New geneartion 341mb (client mode: 113)
eden 315 (client mode: 104)
Survivors 12 (client mode:4)</programlisting></para>

      <para><programlisting format="linespecific">Setup with 1G and -server -XX:NewRatio=2 -XX:SurvivorRatio=6
Old generation 682mb
New geneartion 341mb
eden 255
Survivors 42</programlisting></para>

      <para>When you want to monitor the heap usage on a production server
      then you could use -Xloggc:/log/gc.log. The GC statistics will be
      written to this file with no overhead. GCViewer can generate a nice
      graph of the logfile (<ulink
      url="http://www.tagtraum.com/gcviewer.html">http://www.tagtraum.com/gcviewer.html</ulink>)</para>

      <para>Another tool which is very handy, and maybe even an absolute
      necessity, is jvmstat. Jvmstat shows you graphically how your memory is
      filled between permanent, old and young generation, It also shows how
      eden and survivor spaces are filled.</para>

      <para>There are many articles on the Internet with more information on
      memory and heap size tuning on different platforms. See for example
      <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/performance/">
      http://java.sun.com/performance/</ulink></para>
    </section>

    <section id="appserver">
      <title>Application server</title>

      <para>Every application server contains a number of OOTB
      (out-of-the-box) performance-related parameters that can be fine-tuned
      depending on your environment and applications. Tuning these parameters
      based on your system requirements (rather than running with default
      settings) can greatly improve performance and the scalability of an
      application.</para>

      <para>Modify the value of the http listener threads.</para>

      <para>Application servers can service multiple simultaneous requests and
      because thread creation is expensive application servers have to
      maintain a pool of threads that handle each request. Some application
      servers break this thread pool into two: one to handle the incoming
      requests and place those in a queue and one to take the threads from the
      queue and do the actual work requested by the caller. Regardless of the
      implementation, the size of the thread pool limits the amount of work
      your application server can do; the tradeoff is that there is a point at
      which the context-switching (giving the CPU to each of the threads in
      turn) becomes so costly that performance degrades.</para>

      <para>Some other things you might consider:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Turn off excessive logging, because this could significantly
          slow system performance.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Disable checks for JSP page checks and servlet
          reloading.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Precompile JSPs</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para></para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="mmbase">
    <title>MMBase optimization</title>

    <section id="mmbase_caches">
      <title>Caches</title>

      <para>MMBase relies heavily on its caches. Most caches are configurable
      in the caches.xml, which is in the root of the MMBase configuration.
      There are a few which have a large effect on memory usage and database
      round trips. The MMBase admin has a page where cache statistics are
      shown. This page shows how efficient a cache is.</para>

      <para>The default implementation of all caches is a Least Recently Used
      Hashtable. Another implementation can be plugged in when this is not
      sufficient.</para>

      <para>Before explaining these caches it is important to understand the
      two different types of nodes MMbase uses. MMBase has virtual and real
      nodes. Real nodes contain fields which are defined in a builder. Virtual
      nodes are usually a result of a multi level query. Fields in virtual
      nodes are original from multiple builders. The field name is always
      prefixed with the builder name. Real nodes represent objects like news
      items. Virtual nodes represent multiple parts of different objects. A
      virtual node can contain a news item title and the authors full name.
      Virtual nodes do not have a nodenumber.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>'Nodes' cache. This cache is used to store individual real
          nodes. The key of this cache is the nodenumber. All real nodes
          requested are saved in this one.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>'NodeList' cache which stores the results of real node list
          requests. This cache can become very big rapidly. All real nodes
          requested by a list are also stored in the 'Nodes' cache. This cache
          usually keeps references to nodes which are already flushed by the
          'Nodes' cache.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>'Multilevel' cache. This cache stores all results of virtual
          node list requests. This cache stores the results for all
          complicated SearchQueries.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>'AggregatedResult' cache. All results from queries with
          min/max/count fields are stored in this.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>'RelatedNodes' cache. The results in this cache contain nodes
          which are related to another node.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>'Related' cache. The results in this cache are relations which
          belong to a node. The key of the cache is a nodenumber.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>How the caches are used, depends on how the application on top of
      MMbase is coded. An application which uses a lot of getRelatedNodes
      request requires a large 'RelatedNodes' cache. An application with a lot
      of complicated queries with multiple tables involved requires a larger
      'Multilevel' cache.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="sequence">
    <title>Performance tuning sequence</title>

    <para>We recommend that you tune the production environment in the
    following sequence:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Tuning Your Application and MMBase</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Tuning Application Server</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Tuning the Java Runtime System</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Tuning the Operating System</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Tuning Database Servers</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>When you are done with tuniong thenreverse the order and do it all
    again. Changes in one part will require changes in others.</para>
  </section>
</article>
