<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="managers-mmbase4managers-index">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Running MMBase in your organization</title>

    <date>2002-08</date>

    <edition>$Id$</edition>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Rogier</firstname>

        <surname>Schaaf</surname>

        <affiliation>
          <orgname>E-id! Internet Strategies BV</orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>This software is OSI Certified Open Source Software. OSI Certified
      is a certification mark of the Open Source Initiative.</para>

      <para>The license (Mozilla version 1.0) can be read at the MMBase site.
      See <ulink url="http://www.mmbase.org/license">http://www.mmbase.org/license</ulink></para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <abstract>
    <para>This document offers to technical and non technical people,
    operating at management level, insights in the use of MMBase as a &#39;web
    publishing system&#39; or a &#39;web content management system&#39;. First
    a high level overview of the MMBase product is supplied, followed by a
    short overview of the underlying concepts and technologies. As MMBase is
    an open source product, this document also outlines the consequences that
    come with running open source software in your organization.</para>

    <para>Derived from the open source philosophy, the community thrives
    certain version and release management principles. For potential users and
    decision makers, a clear insight in this process is very important.</para>

    <para>To support the product, a community has been setup. This document
    also covers the organizational structure of this community and its official
    spokesman and their specific roles within the community</para>
  </abstract>

  <section>
    <title>Management summary</title>

    <para>[todo: this section should provide a management summary of the
    overall document]</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>What is MMBase?</title>

    <para>MMBase is a content management system that can be used for
    publishing websites. What is a content management system? What is content?
    Content is stuff that we use to construct websites. As technology
    advanced, websites evolved from simple static &#39;text-like websites&#39;
    to complex multi-media products with streaming media like video and sound.
    All these pieces - text, pictures and video - are considered content and
    should be managed is someway.</para>

    <para>When working with content, eventually every site will feel the need
    for an automated system to manage all these pieces in an easy and user
    friendly way without having to worry about the technological impact of
    each content piece. A content management system offers its users (editors,
    publishers, designers) tailored functions to maintain a website and keep
    its contents alive.</para>

    <para>MMBase in such a system. It covers the whole spectrum needed to:
    import, manage, maintain, export and publish content for your websites. To
    achieve this MMBase contains tools for editorial people to insert and
    maintain web content. To support web designers, MMBase offers an easy to
    learn language for publishing the content to the websites.</para>

    <para>By using MMBase as the content management system for your websites,
    you can separate the content from the way it appears (the design) in your
    websites. The main advantage of separating content and design is that all
    information is stored only once. For example, if you have information on a
    certain product on your website, and the product specs change, you only
    have to change the specs once and all websites that use this information
    will reflect the changes. This is a welcome contrast to
    &#34;hardcoded&#34; webpages, where you might have to review each
    individual web pages to validate the specs.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Features and benefits - the content cloud</title>

      <para>MMBase models its information as objects. MMBase creates objects
      that are a representation of content items and MMBase maintains objects
      that specify the possible relations between these content items. This
      structure results in a web of content pieces and their relations, also
      known in MMBase as &#34;the content cloud&#34;. A music band, for
      example, can have a relation called &#34;plays on&#34; the festival
      called &#34;Pinkpop&#34;, and this relation indicates that the band is
      displayed on the Pinkpop site. If you want to remove the band from the
      site because they do not appear on Pinkpop, you can simply remove the
      relation and the band will not be published on the website anymore. If
      you want to publish the band on another site (with another design), you
      can simply add a relation that indicates that the band needs to be
      displayed on another website.</para>

      <para>The content cloud offers optimal flexibility on use and reuse of
      content, while in the meantime it doesn&#39;t impose any constraints on
      the layout of the site that refers to the content in the cloud. For
      example, you could easily create a large single content cloud and
      publish this cloud, or parts of it, to several different websites, each
      site presenting their own unique layout.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Features and benefits - reusing content</title>

      <para>MMBase strictly separates content from design, which means that
      content can be reused in different designs. When creating a web page,
      for example, you can use HTML tags to create the appropriate design for
      that individual page. By using HTML tags your sites is restricted to the
      possibilities of HTML. Showing the information on an IMode phone or
      publishing it to a PDF document becomes a very tough job. By strictly
      separating content from design, information can be reused in different
      websites, displayed on a different devices, broadcast, sent as e-mail,
      published on an IRC channel, or exported as XML.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Features and benefits - media types and media sources</title>

      <para>Another import aspect of MMBase is that it is able to communicate
      with various types of hardware and software products that are frequently
      used for publishing information like CD players and image scanners. If a
      song of a band has to be published, you can insert a CD into a CD player
      and use your editors to relate a specific track to the band, at which
      point the song will be published on your website. No saving of the CD,
      converting of formats, or copying to a server is necessary. MMBase has
      automated these frequently recurring actions.</para>

      <para>Another example is a photo placed in a scanner. The editors can be
      used to tell MMBase which relations that image has, and you can give the
      image a title and a description. For other actions such as converting
      the image to a JPG, resizing the image is needed. Relating an image with
      a band will cause the website to show that image on the band&#39;s page.</para>

      <para>MMBase integrates a lot of external software. This means that you
      don&#39;t have to encode music file to different file formats, or
      convert image formats, etc. MMBase also contains internal software
      agents that are able to automatically broadcast audio, save audio from
      the radio, check information within MMBase, etc. MMBase has a great deal
      of functionality, and the MMBase community will create more and more of
      this in the future.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Adding content to MMBase</title>

      <para>Information can be added to MMBase in a number of ways, the most
      important of which are the MMBase editors. The MMBase editors allow
      people to insert, manipulate, and delete information. The editors are
      based on a web interface, and can be run in a web browser such as
      Netscape or Internet Explorer.</para>

      <para>The advantage of a web-enabled editor is that you don&#39;t need
      to install additional programs to edit the information, and you can
      maintain the information from any workplace that&#39;s enabled with web
      access. Editors don&#39;t need to have any knowledge of website design.
      They are only involved in the process of managing information.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Publishing content with MMBase</title>

      <para>Graphical designers can publish information maintained within
      MMBase in any format they wish. They can publish the information at a
      website, in multiple websites, on a mobile terminal, in Flash, or can
      broadcast the information maintained by MMBase. MMBase provides a
      language that enable designers to retrieve the MMBase information. The
      information can also be retrieved with other languages, such as PHP, and
      JSP. MMBase can even give the information as XML.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>MMBase organization</title>

    <para>To support the use of MMBase, an organization consisting of several
    entities, each with its own responsibilities has been setup. Key in this
    setup is the Open Source licensing model.</para>

    <section>
      <title>MMBase Community</title>

      <para>The MMBase developer community consist of software engineers doing
      day-to-day development on the MMBase product. They are the core part of
      the MMBase project. Without these people there would be no MMBase
      project. The roles and responsibilities that people assume within the
      project are based on personal merit. Everyone can help regardless of
      their role. However, in order to keep the project manageable, the MMBase
      Developer Community is divided into three roles: the MMBase management
      committee (MMC), the Committers, and the Developers.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>MMBase Management Committee</title>

      <para>The MMBase Management Committee, short the MMC, consists of people
      who have done a lot for MMBase as a product and who have in depth
      knowledge of the product. The MMC coordinates the Open Source process,
      coordinates the MMBase projects, and coordinates which code additions and
      changes will actually be added to the central MMBase code repository.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>MMBase Committers</title>

      <para>MMBase Committers are developers who have frequently added
      valuable code to MMBase. Committers are people who have in-depth
      knowledge of the internal workings of MMBase. Based on this knowledge,
      they have access to the central repository of MMBase and are allowed to
      add new programs to the MMBase repository.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>MMBase Developers</title>

      <para>Developers are all people involved in the MMBase process.
      Developers inform us about bugs and try to solve these bugs. All people
      seriously working on MMBase can obtain the status of developer. If a
      developer frequently submits code that is valuable to MMBase, the status
      of the developer will be upgraded to committer.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>MMBase Foundation</title>

      <para>The MMBase Foundation has initiated the MMBase process, and
      accompanies the MMBase community. The foundation performs tasks needed
      to further mature MMBase as an Open Source project, focusing on task
      that cannot or should not be performed by developers. The foundation has
      two principal tasks. First, the foundation gives presentations on
      MMBase, communicates with the press and act as a central point of
      communication. Second the foundation tries to create an environment in
      which the MMBase developers can flourish. This relates to availability
      of an MMBase website where all relevant information on MMBase is
      centralized (www.mmbase.org), availability of a central repository for
      MMBase programs and documentation. The foundation also provides for the
      site&#39;s hardware.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Configuration Management</title>

    <para>Configuration management of MMBase is currently implemented on a
    best effort basis. This means that there&#39;s no formal requirement by
    the MMBase community to deliver releases according to a predefined release
    schedule.</para>

    <para>All relevant MMBase artifacts, such as program source, compiled
    code, documentation and samples are all maintained in a central
    repository. This repository is based on a common accepted standard (CVS,
    Concurrent Versions Systems) and is read-only accessible for anyone through
    a documented procedure. This approach offers, within the available
    resources of the MMBase community, the best solution for easy spread of
    the MMBase source and object code.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Version and release management and planning</title>

      <para>Although version and release management is performed on a best
      effort basis, the MMBase community targets two to three minor releases
      each year. A minor release is indicated by the dot in the release number
      (for example release 1.6). The latest minor release was release 1.7.</para>

      <para>Conforming to general software practices, the minor releases focus
      primarily on bug fixing and backward compatibility. These issues are
      frequently discussed on the MMBase developer mailing list.</para>

      <para>Planning of new (minor) releases is always communicated through
      the MMBase developer mailing list. Depending on the amount of work, the
      delivery of such a release can be anywhere between a couple of weeks to
      two to three months.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Maintaining backward compatibility</title>

      <para>As MMBase has a growing user community, backwards compatibility is
      a growing issue. As no major release plans have been drawn up yet (e.g.
      a 2.0 release), there&#39;s no experience yet on dealing with backward
      compatibility between major releases.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>MMBase technologies</title>

    <para>MMBase is founded on Java technologies, specifically the J2EE
    flavor of MMBase. This part of Java focuses on delivering the features of
    Java on a server oriented platform. By using Java/J2EE technologies,
    MMBase can run on any platform that supports the Java/J2EE platform.</para>

    <para>Note that it&#39;s a common misconception that Java/J2EE doesn&#39;t
    run on Microsoft platforms. Microsoft&#39;s announcement that it will not
    support Java, has only impact on the availability of Microsoft engineered
    Java support in their operating system. Fortunately other companies, like
    Sun and IBM, offer extensive support for Java and J2EE technologies on the
    Microsoft Windows platforms, on clients as well as on servers.</para>

    <section>
      <title>MMBase Architecture</title>

      <para>MMBase has a layered architecture. Each layer in this architecture
      has its own responsibilities. For example the core layer of MMBase is
      responsible for access to the database. Through this approach it&#39;s
      fairly easy to add additional support for new databases or extend support
      for specific features in specific databases.</para>

      <para>To gain more insight in the actual layering of the architecture,
      an graphical overview of the architecture is provided.</para>

      <graphic fileref="media/architecture.png" />

      <para>In the above picture, the green components are plugin-like parts
      of MMBase. By using a common set of access points and negotiating the
      security layer of MMBase, these plugins can actually communicate with
      the core components of MMBase. Samples of core components are for
      example the actual content elements (nodes) stored in MMBase.</para>

      <para>Using the plugin structure, the base functionality of MMBase can
      be extended without having impact on the other components. This is an
      important feature and benefit of the layered architecture of MMBase.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Java</title>

      <para>The core components of MMBase are implemented using Java server
      software. An important benefit of this technology is that these
      components are scalable &#34;by design&#34;. What does this mean? This
      means that websites, implemented with MMBase as content management
      system, can scale up without the need for additional programming. Of
      course your machine running your MMBase website will eventually run out
      of CPU cycles as it processes more and more visitors. But, without
      having to change a line of MMBase code, you can easily add additional
      hardware to beef up your site&#39;s performance. This ability is
      inherent to the Java/J2EE technologies used by MMBase.</para>

      <para>To be able to run MMBase and benefit from this scalability
      feature, you have to have a runtime server component, also known as an
      Application Server. There are several commercial products available
      (IBM&#39;s WebSphere or BEA&#39;s WebLogic), but also Open Source
      products are available. Currently the Tomcat product from the Jakarta
      organization is a popular and robust product to run your MMBase
      websites.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Technologies for Page designers</title>

      <para>Eventually, when you collected content for your website,
      you&#39;ll want to publish this content to your website in an attractive
      way. This is typically the moment the page or template designer comes
      in.</para>

      <para>MMBase has a comprehensive set of tags (a.k.a. the MMBase Tag
      Library) that support page designers in retrieving content from MMBase.
      These tags are comparable to the standard HTML used to build a static
      webpage. The major difference is that by using the MMBase tags, you can
      spice up your pages with content available in MMBase like images,
      up-to-date news items provided by news editors or even streaming media
      like music or video.</para>

      <para>The learning curve for page designers proficient with HTML covers
      probably not more than 5 to 10 days depending on their experience. To
      get up to speed quickly, there&#39;s a tutorial available for page
      designers on how to apply this technology.</para>

      <para>The MMBase Tag Library is based on the JSP Tag Lib technology, a
      common technology used to develop dynamic websites in a Java/J2EE
      environment.</para>

      <para>By offering this library, it&#39;s also possible to integrate the
      development of websites with MMBase in popular page design tools like
      Dreamweaver by Macromedia.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Technologies for Editors</title>

      <para>[todo: This section focuses on the availability of editors, edit
      wizards and the possibility of &#34;easy customization&#34; of these
      tools.]</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Databases</title>

      <para>[todo: Describe the datastores that are available to MMBase to
      store content. Also, briefly describe the pluggable structure of adding
      new, unsupported databases to the list of available database for
      MMBase.]</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Running Open Source software in your organization</title>

    <simpara></simpara>

    <section>
      <title>What is Open Source Software and how can you benefit from it?</title>

      <para>[todo: Here we should elaborate on the principal business benefits
      of running Open Source software in a commercial environment.]</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>MMBase license</title>

      <para>[todo: Add some specifics about the MMBase license and the
      do&#39;s and dont&#39;s that this accompanies.]</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Getting support</title>

      <para>[todo: Supply information on the companies that support MMBase.
      Maybe refer to an addendum where updated profiles of the supporting
      companies are available.]</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Adding your own features to MMBase</title>

      <para>[todo: Describe the possibility of adding features to MMBase or
      customize its working behavior because the full source code is
      available through the OSS license model. Also describe that adding
      features to MMBase can be donated by the author to MMBase, thus
      contributing to the functional richness of the product.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
