<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  

  <articleinfo>
  	<title>Creating webpages with the MMBase Tag Library</title>
	<date>2003-07</date>
 	<edition>$Id: taglib-tutorial.xml,v 1.9 2003-07-27 17:47:52 henk Exp $</edition>
    <copyright>
      <year>This document is created under the Mozilla Public License</year>
    </copyright>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Rogier</firstname>

        <surname>Schaaf (E-id! Internet Strategies B.V.)</surname>
      </author>

      <author>
        <firstname>Michiel</firstname>

        <surname>Meeuwissen</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.1</revnumber>

        <date>2002-08</date>

        <revremark>First draft</revremark>
      </revision>

      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.2</revnumber>

        <date>2003-03</date>

        <revremark>Changed tutorial to use the MyNews application from the
        MMBase distro.</revremark>
      </revision>

      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.3</revnumber>
		<date>2003-07</date>
        <revremark>Completed tutorial for MyNews application and reworked comments
        from Documentation projectgroup.</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>

    <abstract>
      <para>This document offers a tutorial for page designer who want to
      build web pages using the MMBase Tag Library. Readers should be familiar
      with JSP technologies, HTML and have an up-and-running instance of
      MMBase available.</para>
    </abstract>
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>In this tutorial we try to give page designers a hands-on overview
    of the capabilities of the MMBase Tag Library. This technology, shipped
    with the MMBase content management system, enables page designers in
    developing web pages that retrieve their content from the MMBase system.
    After reading this tutorial and working your way through the examples we
    hope that share our enthusiasm for the MMBase system and the possibilities
    it offers to page designers.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Who should read this tutorial?</title>

      <para>This tutorial is aimed at page designers who develop websites
      using MMBase as the underlying content management system. To successful
      complete this tutorial, you must be proficient with HTML and JSP
      concepts like tags and tag libraries.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>What you need to complete this tutorial?</title>

      <para>This tutorial requires a working instance of MMBase with an empty
      cloud available. The name of the cloud is &#34;MMBase&#34;. If you
      don&#39;t have an MMBase instance available in your network, ask your
      MMBase administrator to set one up for you.</para>

      <para>To edit your pages you&#39;ll need at least some breed of editor.
      The tutorial makes no assumptions on your tooling. You can edit your
      pages with your favorite editor, however the tutorial doesn&#39;t
      elaborate on using specific tools for page editing.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Conventions</title>

      <para>We have used a number of styles of text and layout in this
      tutorial to help differentiate between different kinds of information.
      The following examples are an example of this markup.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Example</title>

        <para>All examples in this tutorial are separately headed</para>
      </example>

      <caution>
        <para>this indicates a possible problem area</para>
      </caution>

      <warning>
        <para>this indicates a warning</para>
      </warning>

      <important>
        <para>important notices</para>
      </important>

      <note>
        <para>additional information</para>
      </note>

      <tip>
        <para>this indicates a valuable tip</para>
      </tip>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Tell us what you think</title>

      <para>The MMBase community has worked hard on this tutorial to make it
      enjoyable and useful. Our best reward would be to hear from you that you
      liked working through it and it helped you discovering the possibilities
      of the MMBase tag library.</para>

      <para>Please let us know what you think about it. Tell us what you liked
      best and what aspects of this tutorial you didn&#39;t like so we improve
      future releases of this document. The easiest way to give us feedback is
      to drop an email message at:</para>

      <remark><email>documentation@mmbase.org</email></remark>

      <para>You can also find more information about MMBase on the MMBase
      website. There you&#39;ll find sample code, information on latest
      releases, currently running projects and their participating members and
      lots of other interesting information. The address of the website is:</para>

      <remark><link>http://www.mmbase.org</link></remark>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Getting help</title>

      <para>If you find a mistake in this tutorial, please inform us about it
      at <link>documentation@mmbase.org</link>.</para>

      <para>If you have additional questions please contact one of the
      companies that support MMBase. You will find a complete listing of
      supporting companies on the MMBase website. Point your browser to:</para>

      <remark><link>http://www.mmbase.org</link></remark>

      <para>Furthermore, you can subscribe to several mailing lists where
      users and developers exchange information. Good chance you&#39;ll find
      someone there willing to help you out.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Preparing the tutorial</title>

    <para>This tutorial builds the MyNews application, a sample application
    that is shipped with the MMBase distribution. Before beginning this
    tutorial, make sure that you have the distribution of MMBase installed and
    running with the demo applications running as well. The MyNews application
    uses the following content model. Take a minute to review this design as
    it will be used throughout this tutorial.</para>

    <figure>
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="media/cloud.jpg"
      format="JPEG"></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>As you can see, the central item appears to be our news item. It has
    several relations to other content types within the cloud, some of them
    showing a &#34;posrel&#34; attribute.</para>

    <para>These are special types of relations. Posrel relations offer the
    possibility to add sequencing information on the relation. This way you
    can set the sequence as each relation is added by using an integer
    attribute. Note that setting the &#34;pos&#34; attribute of a posrel
    relation is not done automatically. If you don&#39;t supply a value,
    MMBase will set it to its default value being -1.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Accessing content stored in MMBase</title>

    <para>When you&#39;re developing websites with MMBase as the underlying
    content management system, your pages will need access to the content that
    is stored in MMBase. Content in MMBase is stored in a cloud. Within the
    cloud you&#39;ll find nodes. The nodes are the actual pieces of content in
    MMBase. Nodes are organized in content types and relations between content
    types. For example, if you define that every news item you publish on your
    website would contain the news text and an image, then you would have two
    content types in your cloud: content type &#34;news&#34; and content type
    &#34;images&#34;. Furthermore you would define a relation between the
    content types news and image to support displaying images with newsitems.</para>

    <para>For a very basic website you&#39;ll need no more than a handful of
    content types. The standard MMBase distribution is supplied with all
    necessary node types for a basic website.</para>

    <para>Now let&#39;s have a look at how we can access the cloud from within
    the default J2EE templating facility, e.g. Java Server Pages or short
    JSP&#39;s. To access the content cloud, MMBase supplies developers with a
    tag library. We assume you are familiar with the concepts of such a
    library and will not elaborate on it here.</para>

    <para>Every tag library uses it&#39;s own namespace. The namespace is
    there to help the system distinguish between different tags from different
    libraries. MMBase tags are all prefixed by default with the string
    &#34;mm&#34;. You are free to choose another prefix, however this usage is
    very common across MMBase developers.</para>

    <para>To prepare your pages to work with MMBase tag libraries the first
    thing you&#39;ll have todo is to declare the MMBase tag library in your
    page. The MMBase tag library is declared by the following statement:</para>

    <programlisting>&#60;%@ taglib uri=&#34;http://www.mmbase.org/mmbase-taglib-1.0&#34; prefix=&#34;mm&#34; %&#62;</programlisting>

    <para>In this declaration you tell the JSP compiler that you will be using
    the MMBase taglibrary and that the tags used by this library are prefixed
    by &#34;mm&#34;. The value for the uri attribute, in this case
    &#34;http://www.mmbase.org/mmbase-taglib-1.0&#34; is the identification of
    the MMBase tag library and should correspond to the entry in the web.xml
    file of your web container configuration. Your WEB.XML should contain the
    following entry:</para>

    <programlisting>&#60;!-- MMBase tag library --&#62;
&#60;taglib&#62;
  &#60;taglib-uri&#62;http://www.mmbase.org/mmbase-taglib-1.0&#60;/taglib-uri&#62;
  &#60;taglib-location&#62;/WEB-INF/mmbase-taglib.tld&#60;/taglib-location&#62;
&#60;/taglib&#62;
</programlisting>

    <para>In the default MMBase distro, this is all preconfigured for you.
    Have a look at the file web.xml in the WEB-INF directory. Look for the
    entry mmbase-taglib. This entry tells your application server that
    you&#39;ll be using this library in your JSP&#39;s. Furthermore, the
    classes that are used by the mmbase taglib are packaged together with the
    MMBase core code, but if you inspect the file mmbase.jar with a ZIP tool,
    you&#39;ll notice the taglib classes.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Importing the default magazine</title>

      <para>To start with this tutorial, we will first start the actual MyNews
      application. Find the URL on the examples screen and click it to startup
      MyNews. MyNews should present you it&#39;s first screen.</para>

      <para>[todo:screendump]</para>

      <para>This first screen shows the magazine that&#39;s available in the
      demo setup of MMBase, together with the news items associated with that
      magazine and (full right) a link you can click to read the actual news
      item. As you can see, the layout is straightforward without graphics.
      We&#39;ll focus on developing this page first, then you can add graphics
      and layout to your liking.</para>

      <para>Below, in the lefthand corner of the screen, you&#39;ll find two
      links. Clicking the last link will show you the source of this page.</para>

      <para>The MyNews application runs with a simple database with a single
      magazine in it. The designers of the database have labeled this
      magazine with a default alias named &#34;default.mags&#34;. To use this
      default magazine we import it into our page by using the
      &#60;mm:import&#62; tag. The &#60;mm:import&#62; tag creates a special
      environment, called a context. Into this context, the developer can
      store identifiers and their values (Java developers can compare a
      context to a Hashmap like structure). </para>

      <programlisting>&#60;%@taglib uri=&#34;http://www.mmbase.org/mmbase-taglib-1.0&#34; prefix=&#34;mm&#34; %&#62;
&#60;mm:import externid=&#34;magid&#34;&#62;default.mags&#60;/mm:import&#62;</programlisting>

      <para>When this page would be called with the parameter magid in the
      request then the value of magid would be passed to the id magid. For
      example if index.jsp is called with index.jsp?magid=210 then the id
      magid would have the value 210. For this to work you will for example
      have to create a page with links to all available magazines, like &#60;a
      href=&#34;index.jsp?magid=210&#34;&#62;The default magazine&#60;/a&#62;.
      In the &#34;Working with related nodes&#34; we will see how you can
      create such page by using the &#60;mm:url /&#62; tag.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Accessing the cloud</title>

      <para>Any webpage that tries to access content from MMBase will first
      have to initialize access to the cloud. For cloud initialization the
      &#60;mm:cloud&#62; tag is available. Besides a number of exceptions, the
      &#60;mm:cloud&#62; tag encapsulates all other MMBase tags you want to
      use. This means that all other MMBase tags you&#39;ll want to use, must
      appear between the &#60;mm: cloud&#62; and &#60;/mm:cloud&#62; tags.
      Note that you get compiler errors when you place tags outside the cloud
      tag.</para>

      <example>
        <para>When using the &#60;mm:cloud&#62; tag there are several
        attributes that you can use. For now, we only use the &#34;name&#34;
        attribute. By default MMBase uses the &#34;mmbase&#34; value for this
        attribute if you omit it. If you want to access a cloud that has
        another name, you&#39;ll have to supply this name to be able to access
        that cloud.</para>

        <para>Please refer to the MMBase Tag Library Reference Guide to get a
        full overview of the possible attributes you can use with this tag.</para>

        <para><tip><para>The &#60;mm:cloud&#62; tag offers far more
        functionality that presented here. To learn more about the
        &#60;mm:cloud&#62; tag, please refer to the advanced features section
        of the tutorial where you can learn about using the authentication
        features of this tag. [ TO DO]</para></tip></para>

        <para>To access the cloud, add the following tags to our page:</para>

        <programlisting>&#60;%@taglib
        uri=&#34;http://www.mmbase.org/mmbase-taglib-1.0&#34;
        prefix=&#34;mm&#34; %&#62; &#60;mm:import
        externid=&#34;magid&#34;&#62;default.mags&#60;/mm:import&#62;
        &#60;mm:cloud name=&#34;mmbase&#34;&#62; &#60;/mm:cloud&#62;</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Working with node tags</title>

      <para>Through the tag in the previous chapter, the &#60;mm:cloud&#62;
      tag, we gained access to the MMBase cloud. Next we want access to our
      magazine, a node in the MMBase cloud.</para>

      <para>Now to access our magazine, you&#39;ll have to tell MMBase which
      node you wish to access. Every node within MMBase is automatically
      assigned a unique number to distinguish it from other nodes.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>To make your content portable between databases, you can use
        aliases to refer to your nodes, in stead of absolute numerical node
        numbers. As you transfer content between databases it&#39;s not
        guaranteed that nodes receive the same number, while they always keep
        an assigned alias. Usage of aliases will also make your JSP&#39;s
        better readable.</para>
      </tip>

      <para>To retrieve a node from MMBase you use the &#60;mm:node&#62; tag.</para>

      <para>To retrieve our magazine we obviously have three alternate
      approaches. We can use the number of the node, we can use the alias that
      is linked to our magazine, or we can use an id which contains the node
      number or the alias as its value. From the previous paragraph we know
      that our magazine has a default alias of &#34;default.mags&#34;.
      We&#39;ll use that to access it in our JSP. Add the following to our JSP:</para>

      <programlisting>&#60;%@taglib uri=&#34;http://www.mmbase.org/mmbase-taglib-1.0&#34; prefix=&#34;mm&#34; %&#62;

&#60;mm:import externid=&#34;magid&#34;&#62;default.mags&#60;/mm:import&#62;
&#60;mm:cloud name=&#34;mmbase&#34;&#62;
  &#60;mm:node number=&#34;$magid&#34;&#62;
  &#60;/mm:node&#62;
&#60;/mm:cloud&#62;</programlisting>

      <para>Using the &#60;mm:node&#62; tag we actually are accessing the node
      of which we imported the alias or node number earlier into our page,
      using the &#60;mm:import&#62; tag. By using the $ directive, MMBase
      knows that the value between quotes is not an actual value of an alias,
      but an imported variable within the context of this page.</para>

      <para>Another approach, if our database would ever only contain one
      default magazine, would be to lookup its node number in MMBase and refer
      it directly in our page. For example, assume we one magazine in our
      database with number 210, we could do:</para>

      <programlisting>&#60;%@taglib uri=&#34;http://www.mmbase.org/mmbase-taglib-1.0&#34; prefix=&#34;mm&#34; %&#62;

&#60;mm:cloud name=&#34;mmbase&#34;&#62;
  &#60;mm:node number=&#34;210&#34;&#62;
  &#60;/mm:node&#62;
&#60;/mm:cloud&#62;</programlisting>

      <para>The obvious drawback of this structure is that the magazine number
      is now hardcoded into our page, which means we can only show this
      specific magazine.</para>

      <para> An alternative to working with &#60;mm:import
      externid=&#34;magid&#34; /&#62; is to use a little Java scriplet inside
      your template which distills the node number from the request.</para>

      <programlisting>&#60;%@taglib uri=&#34;http://www.mmbase.org/mmbase-taglib-1.0&#34; prefix=&#34;mm&#34; %&#62;

&#60;%
  String magid = (String) request.getAttribute(&#34;magid&#34;);
%&#62;

&#60;mm:cloud name=&#34;mmbase&#34;&#62;
  &#60;mm:node number=&#34;&#60;%= magid%&#62;&#34;&#62;
  &#60;/mm:node&#62;
&#60;/mm:cloud&#62;</programlisting>

      <para>These are all alternatives to the solution presented in the sample
      MMBase application MyNews. Your actual choice depends on your
      application needs and your personal liking. For this tutorial we will
      stick to the default implementation as presented in the MMBase
      distribution.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Summary</title>

      <para>We have now prepared our first JSP that will retrieve a default
      magazine from our preloaded content cloud. We used the
      &#60;mm:import&#62; tag to import our magazine into a context and later
      used the &#60;mm:node&#62; tag to retrieve the magazine from this
      context. Before we could use the &#60;mm:node&#62; tag however, we had
      to tell MMBase which cloud we are going to access. Accessing the cloud
      is the important step you always have to perform to work with MMBase
      content in a JSP environment.</para>

      <para>In the next chapter we&#39;ll try to display some of the fields of
      the magazine and display the titles of the available newsitems
      associated with the magazine.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Working with field tags</title>

    <para>MMBase organizes its content into nodes. Each node consists of
    several fields, containing the actual content of the node. Each field can
    be of a specific type. To access the fields within a node, MMBase offers
    the &#60;mm:field&#62; tag. To access the title and the subtitle of the
    magazine, we tell MMBase to display it by using this tag.</para>

    <para>In our first page we&#39;ll now use the &#60;mm:field&#62; tag to
    display fields from the default magazine. Create a table and within the
    table, create two rows. The first row displays the title and the subtitle
    of the default magazine. The second row display the intro and the body of
    the magazine. Your page should now look something like the listing below.</para>

    <programlisting>&#60;%@taglib uri=&#34;http://www.mmbase.org/mmbase-taglib-1.0&#34; prefix=&#34;mm&#34; %&#62;

&#60;mm:import externid=&#34;magid&#34;&#62;default.mags&#60;/mm:import&#62;
&#60;mm:cloud name=&#34;mmbase&#34;&#62;
  &#60;mm:node number=&#34;$magid&#34; id=&#34;mag&#34;&#62;
    &#60;table&#62;
      &#60;tr&#62;
        &#60;td&#62;
          &#60;h1&#62;&#60;mm:field name=&#34;title&#34;/&#62;&#60;/h1&#62;&#60;br/&#62;
          &#60;h2&#62;&#60;mm:field name=&#34;subtitle&#34;/&#62;&#60;/h2&#62;
        &#60;/td&#62;
      &#60;/tr&#62;
      &#60;tr&#62;
        &#60;td&#62;
          &#60;mm:field  name=&#34;intro&#34;/&#62;&#60;br/&#62;
          &#60;mm:field  name=&#34;html(body)&#34;/&#62;
        &#60;/td&#62;
      &#60;/tr&#62;
    &#60;/table&#62;
  &#60;/mm:node&#62;
&#60;/mm:cloud&#62;</programlisting>

    <para>Note that we created a table, and inside the table we used the
    &#60;mm:field&#62; tag to display the title and the subtitle of the
    magazine. As a simple formatting option we added &#60;h1&#62; and
    &#60;h2&#62; tags to create the impression of titles. Also notice that all
    MMBase tags are well formed. This means that opening and closing tags
    should always be in balance. JSP compilers are not as forgiving as
    browsers. If your tags are not well formed, you will definitely see
    compile errors in your log. If you see them, correct the errors and try
    compiling the page again.</para>

    <para>Your page is now ready for a first test and should display the
    title, subtitle, intro and body of the default magazine from the MMBase
    content cloud.</para>

    <para>The &#60;mm:node&#62; tag offers more options than the one shown in
    this tutorial. Please refer to the full documentation for more information
    on the use of this tag.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Working with related nodes</title>

    <para>Next we want to display the news items that can be found in our
    magazine. Refer back to the content model we displayed earlier in this
    tutorial. One related node from magazine is news. As we have the magazine
    available in our page, we should be able to access its related news nodes.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Retrieving the related nodes</title>

      <para>To retrieve related nodes from a specific node, MMBase supplies
      the &#60;mm:related&#62; tag. Within this tag you can use several
      interesting options to control the way MMBase retrieves the related
      nodes. Refer to the full reference documentation to review all possible
      options to control retrieval of related nodes. For now we add an entry
      to our JSP where we tell MMBase to travel a path between our magazine
      and its news using the posrel relation. As we are only interested in the
      sequence of the relation and the title of each news item in our
      magazine, we tell MMBase to only use the &#34;pos&#34; field from the
      posrel relation and the title from the magazine node. We conclude by
      telling MMBase to order all results by the value in the &#34;pos&#34;
      field, thus retrieving each news node in same sequence as it was
      entered.</para>

      <para><programlisting>&#60;mm:related path=&#34;posrel,news&#34; fields=&#34;posrel.pos,news.title&#34; orderby=&#34;posrel.pos&#34;&#62;</programlisting></para>

      <para>When you add the above entry, your JSP should now look something
      like below. Note that we also added a &#60;tr&#62; &#60;/tr&#62; entry,
      so that for each found related node from magazine to news, a new row in
      our table will be created.</para>

      <programlisting>&#60;%@taglib uri=&#34;http://www.mmbase.org/mmbase-taglib-1.0&#34; prefix=&#34;mm&#34; %&#62;

&#60;mm:import externid=&#34;magid&#34;&#62;default.mags&#60;/mm:import&#62;
&#60;mm:cloud name=&#34;mmbase&#34;&#62;
  &#60;mm:node number=&#34;$magid&#34; id=&#34;mag&#34;&#62;
    &#60;table&#62;
      &#60;tr&#62;
        &#60;td&#62;
          &#60;h1&#62;&#60;mm:field name=&#34;title&#34;/&#62;&#60;/h1&#62;&#60;br/&#62;
          &#60;h2&#62;&#60;mm:field name=&#34;subtitle&#34;/&#62;&#60;/h2&#62;
        &#60;/td&#62;
      &#60;/tr&#62;
      &#60;tr&#62;
        &#60;td&#62;
          &#60;mm:field  name=&#34;intro&#34;/&#62;&#60;br/&#62;
          &#60;mm:field  name=&#34;html(body)&#34;/&#62;
        &#60;/td&#62;
      &#60;/tr&#62;
      &#60;tr&#62;
        &#60;td&#62;
          &#60;table&#62;
            &#60;mm:related path=&#34;posrel,news&#34; fields=&#34;posrel.pos,news.title&#34; orderby=&#34;posrel.pos&#34;&#62;
              &#60;tr&#62;
              &#60;/tr&#62;
            &#60;/mm:related&#62;
          &#60;/table&#62;
        &#60;/td&#62;
      &#60;/tr&#62;
    &#60;/table&#62;
  &#60;/mm:node&#62;
&#60;/mm:cloud&#62;</programlisting>

      <note>
        <para>MMBase contains a number of tags by which you can list the nodes
        related to a specific node. Next to &#60;mm:related &#62; you can use
        &#60;mm:relatednodes&#62;, &#60;mm:list&#62; and
        &#60;mm:listnodes&#62;. See the MMBase taglib reference for a
        difference between these tags. </para>
      </note>

      <para>We&#39;ve now setup the basic structure that will create rows for
      each news node found by MMBase. It would be nice though, if these values
      were presented with a heading for each column. We want this heading to
      appear just once before MMBase start writing out the first news node. To
      support this behavior, MMBase has a tag &#60;mm:first&#62; that fires
      upon the first entry in the list.</para>

      <programlisting>&#60;%@taglib uri=&#34;http://www.mmbase.org/mmbase-taglib-1.0&#34; prefix=&#34;mm&#34; %&#62;

&#60;mm:import externid=&#34;magid&#34;&#62;default.mags&#60;/mm:import&#62;
&#60;mm:cloud name=&#34;mmbase&#34;&#62;
  &#60;mm:node number=&#34;$magid&#34; id=&#34;mag&#34;&#62;
    &#60;table&#62;
      &#60;tr&#62;
        &#60;td&#62;
          &#60;h1&#62;&#60;mm:field name=&#34;title&#34;/&#62;&#60;/h1&#62;&#60;br/&#62;
          &#60;h2&#62;&#60;mm:field name=&#34;subtitle&#34;/&#62;&#60;/h2&#62;
        &#60;/td&#62;
      &#60;/tr&#62;
      &#60;tr&#62;
        &#60;td&#62;
          &#60;mm:field  name=&#34;intro&#34;/&#62;&#60;br/&#62;
          &#60;mm:field  name=&#34;html(body)&#34;/&#62;
        &#60;/td&#62;
      &#60;/tr&#62;
      &#60;tr&#62;
        &#60;td&#62;
          &#60;table&#62;
            &#60;mm:related path=&#34;posrel,news&#34; fields=&#34;posrel.pos,news.title&#34; orderby=&#34;posrel.pos&#34;&#62;
              &#60;mm:first&#62;
                &#60;tr&#62;
                  &#60;td&#62;Title&#60;/td&#62;
                  &#60;td/&#62;
                &#60;/tr&#62;
              &#60;/mm:first&#62;
              &#60;tr&#62;
              &#60;/tr&#62;
            &#60;/mm:related&#62;
          &#60;/table&#62;
        &#60;/td&#62;
      &#60;/tr&#62;
    &#60;/table&#62;
  &#60;/mm:node&#62;
&#60;/mm:cloud&#62;</programlisting>

      <para>To complete our JSP, we now have to add the title field followed
      by an URL to the next JSP that will display our actual news. Displaying
      the title is achieved by using the &#60;mm:field&#62; tag again.
      Remember we used this tag to display the some fields from the default
      magazine.</para>

      <programlisting>&#60;%@taglib uri=&#34;http://www.mmbase.org/mmbase-taglib-1.0&#34; prefix=&#34;mm&#34; %&#62;

&#60;mm:import externid=&#34;magid&#34;&#62;default.mags&#60;/mm:import&#62;
&#60;mm:cloud name=&#34;mmbase&#34;&#62;
  &#60;mm:node number=&#34;$magid&#34; id=&#34;mag&#34;&#62;
    &#60;table&#62;
      &#60;tr&#62;
        &#60;td&#62;
          &#60;h1&#62;&#60;mm:field name=&#34;title&#34;/&#62;&#60;/h1&#62;&#60;br/&#62;
          &#60;h2&#62;&#60;mm:field name=&#34;subtitle&#34;/&#62;&#60;/h2&#62;
        &#60;/td&#62;
      &#60;/tr&#62;
      &#60;tr&#62;
        &#60;td&#62;
          &#60;mm:field  name=&#34;intro&#34;/&#62;&#60;br/&#62;
          &#60;mm:field  name=&#34;html(body)&#34;/&#62;
        &#60;/td&#62;
      &#60;/tr&#62;
      &#60;tr&#62;
        &#60;td&#62;
          &#60;table&#62;
            &#60;mm:related path=&#34;posrel,news&#34; fields=&#34;posrel.pos,news.title&#34; orderby=&#34;posrel.pos&#34;&#62;
              &#60;mm:first&#62;
                &#60;tr&#62;
                  &#60;td&#62;Title&#60;/td&#62;
                  &#60;td/&#62;
                &#60;/tr&#62;
              &#60;/mm:first&#62;
              &#60;tr&#62;
                &#60;td&#62;
                  &#60;mm:field name=&#34;title&#34;/&#62;
                &#60;/td&#62;
                &#60;td&#62;
                  &#60;a href=&#39;&#60;mm:url referids=&#34;magid&#34; page=&#34;newsitem.jsp&#34;&#62;
                    &#60;mm:param name=&#34;newsid&#34;&#62;
                      &#60;mm:field name=&#34;number&#34;/&#62;
                    &#60;/mm:param&#62;&#60;/mm:url&#62;&#39;&#62;link
                  &#60;/a&#62;
              &#60;/tr&#62;
            &#60;/mm:related&#62;
          &#60;/table&#62;
        &#60;/td&#62;
      &#60;/tr&#62;
    &#60;/table&#62;
  &#60;/mm:node&#62;
&#60;/mm:cloud&#62;</programlisting>

      <para>The construction of the URL to access the content of the news
      items may seem a bit obscure and needs some additional explanation. First
      we start creation of a default URL by using the &#60;a&#62; tag. In
      stead of hardcoding our &#34;href&#34;, we use data from MMBase by
      letting MMBase create the URL use by using the &#60;mm:url&#62; tag.
      Read the full documentation on this tag to get more information on the
      possibilities of this tag. In this situation the URL is pointing to the
      JSP named &#34;newsitem.jsp&#34;. Within the &#60;mm:url&#62; tag we use
      the &#60;mm:param&#62; tag to pass necessary information to our
      &#34;newsitem.jsp&#34;, namely the number or id of the newsitem we wish
      to read.</para>

      <para>The resulting URL will appear as follows in our browser:</para>

      <programlisting>http://yourhostname/mmbase-webapp/mmexamples/jsp/mynews/newsitem.jsp
  ?magid=default.mags&#38;newsid=59</programlisting>

      <para>When we run our JSP in our browser we should see the following
      page appear [TO DO add screenshot]:</para>

      <graphic fileref="media/mynews.jpg" />
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Constructing the newsitems page</title>

    <para>We&#39;ve completed the first part of our sample application. Next
    we will expand our sample application with a second page that&#39;s
    capable of presenting the news item selected from the first page. First we
    add some familiar stuff like the reference to the MMBase tag library. You
    should incorporate this on every page, otherwise the MMBase tags will
    definitely not work. In this page you see a new feature: the usage of an
    error page. This has nothing to do with MMBase, but is a typical feature
    of the JSP specs. Using an error page, you can create a more elegant way
    to trap unforeseen situations. In stead of presenting the user with a
    stack trace, we can now present an error page where we handle the error
    more gracefully. Building the error page is not within the scope of this
    tutorial, so please review the page yourself if you want to find out more
    about this technique.</para>

    <warning>
      <para>When developing new pages you should be very careful with using
      an error page. Where you want elegant error messages once your website
      is in production, you will surely enjoy the full error message when you
      are developing your JSP-templates.</para>
    </warning>

    <programlisting>&#60;%@page errorPage=&#34;error.jsp&#34; language=&#34;java&#34; contentType=&#34;text/html; charset=UTF-8&#34; %&#62;
&#60;%@taglib uri=&#34;http://www.mmbase.org/mmbase-taglib-1.0&#34; prefix=&#34;mm&#34; %&#62;

&#60;mm:cloud name=&#34;mmbase&#34;&#62;
  &#60;mm:import externid=&#34;newsid&#34; required=&#34;true&#34; /&#62;

  &#60;html&#62;
    &#60;head&#62;
      &#60;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34; href=&#34;style.css&#34; /&#62;
    &#60;/head&#62;

    &#60;mm:node number=&#34;$newsid&#34;&#62;
    &#60;/mm:node&#62;

  &#60;/html&#62;
&#60;/mm:cloud&#62;

</programlisting>

    <para>We import the id of the selected news item from the previous page.
    This value was passed to our new page through the &#60;mm:param&#62; tag
    and the &#60;mm:import&#62; tags retrieves it again.</para>

    <para>Next we use the &#60;mm:node&#62; tag to be able to process the news
    item that we wish to display. Remember that by using the $ directive we
    don&#39;t actually use that value as the node id, but are referring to a
    variable with that name inside the context.</para>

    <para>Next we&#39;ll add the title for our browser window and build the
    basic table structure that will display our news item.</para>

    <programlisting>&#60;%@page errorPage=&#34;error.jsp&#34; language=&#34;java&#34; contentType=&#34;text/html; charset=UTF-8&#34; %&#62;
&#60;%@taglib uri=&#34;http://www.mmbase.org/mmbase-taglib-1.0&#34; prefix=&#34;mm&#34; %&#62;

&#60;mm:cloud name=&#34;mmbase&#34;&#62;
  &#60;mm:import externid=&#34;newsid&#34; required=&#34;true&#34; /&#62;
  &#60;mm:node number=&#34;$newsid&#34;&#62;
 
    &#60;html&#62;
      &#60;head&#62;
        &#60;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34; href=&#34;style.css&#34; /&#62;
        &#60;title&#62;&#60;mm:field  name=&#34;title&#34;/&#62;&#60;/title&#62;
      &#60;/head&#62;

      &#60;body&#62;
      &#60;center&#62;
        &#60;table width=&#34;90%&#34; cellspacing=1 cellpadding=3 border=0&#62;
          &#60;tr&#62;
            &#60;th colspan=&#34;2&#34;&#62;  
              &#60;h2&#62;&#60;mm:field  name=&#34;title&#34;/&#62;&#60;/h2&#62;
                &#60;mm:field name=&#34;subtitle&#34;&#62;
                  &#60;mm:isnotempty&#62;
                    &#60;h3&#62;&#60;mm:write /&#62;&#60;/h3&#62;
                  &#60;/mm:isnotempty&#62;
                &#60;/mm:field&#62;
            &#60;/th&#62;
          &#60;/tr&#62;
        &#60;/table&#62;
      &#60;/center&#62;
    &#60;/html&#62;
  &#60;/mm:node&#62;
&#60;/mm:cloud&#62;</programlisting>

    <para>We see here also the &#39;isnotempty&#39; tag. The
    &#39;isnotempty&#39; tag searches for a parent tag of the type
    &#39;Writer&#39;. Every tag that can produce content, is a Writer tag. The
    field tag is a simple example of a Writer tag. The isnotempy tag now
    checks if the content produced by this parent &#39;writer&#39; tag is
    empty, and in that case it does not evaluate its body.</para>

    <para>We should be aware that a writer tag does <emphasis>not</emphasis>
    write anything to the page by itself if it has a body. The idea is that
    the tags in the body do something with the content provided by the writer
    then.</para>

    <para>So, in this case the content is checked for emptyness, and if not,
    &#39;&#60;h3&#62;&#60;mm:write /&#62;&#60;/h3&#62;&#39; is performed. A
    write-tag without attributes, searches for a parent &#39;writer&#39; and
    writes the content to the page (unless, of course, it has a body, because
    a write-tag is a writer too).</para>

    <para>But in this case, the write-tag does not have a body, so it writes
    the field. The whole exercise was only done to avoid writing empty
    h3-tags to the page if by change the subtitle field of the news items is
    empty. As you saw, this happens because those h3 tags are inside the
    isnotempty-tag too, so will be skipped if the parent writer tag (the
    field) is empty.</para>

    <para>The next step is to complete our full news item in this page.</para>

    <programlisting>&#60;%@page errorPage=&#34;error.jsp&#34; language=&#34;java&#34; contentType=&#34;text/html; charset=UTF-8&#34; %&#62;
&#60;%@taglib uri=&#34;http://www.mmbase.org/mmbase-taglib-1.0&#34; prefix=&#34;mm&#34; %&#62;

&#60;mm:cloud name=&#34;mmbase&#34;&#62;
  &#60;mm:import externid=&#34;newsid&#34; required=&#34;true&#34; /&#62;
  &#60;mm:node number=&#34;$newsid&#34;&#62;
 
    &#60;html&#62;
      &#60;head&#62;
        &#60;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34; href=&#34;style.css&#34; /&#62;
        &#60;title&#62;&#60;mm:field  name=&#34;title&#34;/&#62;&#60;/title&#62;
      &#60;/head&#62;

      &#60;body&#62;
      &#60;center&#62;
        &#60;table width=&#34;90%&#34; cellspacing=1 cellpadding=3 border=0&#62;
          &#60;tr&#62;
            &#60;th colspan=&#34;2&#34;&#62;  
              &#60;h2&#62;&#60;mm:field  name=&#34;title&#34;/&#62;&#60;/h2&#62;
                &#60;mm:field name=&#34;subtitle&#34;&#62;
                  &#60;mm:isnotempty&#62;
                    &#60;h3&#62;&#60;mm:write /&#62;&#60;/h3&#62;
                  &#60;/mm:isnotempty&#62;
                &#60;/mm:field&#62;
            &#60;/th&#62;
          &#60;/tr&#62;

          &#60;tr&#62;
            &#60;td width=&#34;30&#34;&#62;&#60;/td&#62;
            &#60;td&#62;
              &#60;b&#62;&#60;mm:field  name=&#34;intro&#34;/&#62;&#60;/b&#62;
              &#60;p&#62;&#60;mm:field  name=&#34;html(body)&#34;/&#62;&#60;/p&#62;
            &#60;/td&#62;
          &#60;/tr&#62;


        &#60;/table&#62;
      &#60;/center&#62;
    &#60;/html&#62;
  &#60;/mm:node&#62;
&#60;/mm:cloud&#62;</programlisting>

    <para>This new code prints out the intro of the news item. As you can see
    from the actual page, this intro appears in bold formatting to make it
    stand out more. Next we write the body of the item. Notice that we use a
    special function here called html(). This is a special MMBase function
    that allows for the creation of HTML from plain text. Refer to [todo] to
    get more information on all available functions and their usage.</para>

    <para>If we go back to our cloud design we know that any news item can be
    related to quite a few other nodes of different types, like magazines and
    authors. It&#39;s important to evaluate the design of your template, so
    that you provide solutions for any possible related node. For example, it
    would be a bad design if your model expresses a relation between a picture
    and a news item while your template is not capable of displaying the
    picture (unless of course this is your explicit decision and your user
    agrees with you).</para>

    <para>From our cloud design it appears that any news item could possibly
    have relations with attachments, images, people, URL&#39;s and MMEvents.
    For this example we will support relations to images, authors (people) and
    URL&#39;s. Other node types are ignored.</para>

    <programlisting>&#60;%@page errorPage=&#34;error.jsp&#34; language=&#34;java&#34; contentType=&#34;text/html; charset=UTF-8&#34; %&#62;
&#60;%@taglib uri=&#34;http://www.mmbase.org/mmbase-taglib-1.0&#34; prefix=&#34;mm&#34; %&#62;

&#60;mm:cloud name=&#34;mmbase&#34;&#62;
  &#60;mm:import externid=&#34;newsid&#34; required=&#34;true&#34; /&#62;
  &#60;mm:node number=&#34;$newsid&#34;&#62;
 
    &#60;html&#62;
      &#60;head&#62;
        &#60;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34; href=&#34;style.css&#34; /&#62;
        &#60;title&#62;&#60;mm:field  name=&#34;title&#34;/&#62;&#60;/title&#62;
      &#60;/head&#62;

      &#60;body&#62;
      &#60;center&#62;
        &#60;table width=&#34;90%&#34; cellspacing=1 cellpadding=3 border=0&#62;
          &#60;tr&#62;
            &#60;th colspan=&#34;2&#34;&#62;  
              &#60;h2&#62;&#60;mm:field  name=&#34;title&#34;/&#62;&#60;/h2&#62;
                &#60;mm:field name=&#34;subtitle&#34;&#62;
                  &#60;mm:isnotempty&#62;
                    &#60;h3&#62;&#60;mm:write /&#62;&#60;/h3&#62;
                  &#60;/mm:isnotempty&#62;
                &#60;/mm:field&#62;
            &#60;/th&#62;
          &#60;/tr&#62;

          &#60;tr&#62;
            &#60;td width=&#34;30&#34;&#62;&#60;/td&#62;
            &#60;td&#62;
              &#60;b&#62;&#60;mm:field  name=&#34;intro&#34;/&#62;&#60;/b&#62;
              &#60;p&#62;&#60;mm:field  name=&#34;html(body)&#34;/&#62;&#60;/p&#62;
            &#60;/td&#62;
          &#60;/tr&#62;

          &#60;mm:relatednodes type=&#34;images&#34; max=&#34;3&#34;&#62;
            &#60;mm:first&#62;
              &#60;tr&#62;
                &#60;th colspan=&#34;2&#34;&#62;Related images&#60;/th&#62;
              &#60;/tr&#62;
            &#60;/mm:first&#62;
            &#60;tr&#62;
              &#60;td&#62;
                &#60;img src=&#34;&#60;mm:image template=&#34;s(200)&#34; /&#62;&#34; alt=&#34;&#60;mm:field name=&#34;title&#34; /&#62;&#34; /&#62;
                &#60;mm:last&#62;
                  &#60;/td&#62;&#60;/tr&#62;
                &#60;/mm:last&#62;
          &#60;/mm:relatednodes&#62;

          &#60;mm:relatednodes type=&#34;urls&#34;&#62;
            &#60;mm:first&#62;
              &#60;tr&#62;
                &#60;th colspan=&#34;2&#34;&#62;Related urls&#60;/th&#62;
              &#60;/tr&#62;
            &#60;/mm:first&#62;
            &#60;a href=&#34;&#60;mm:field name=&#34;url&#34;/&#62;&#34;&#62;&#60;mm:field name=&#34;description&#34;/&#62;&#60;/a&#62;
            &#60;br/&#62;
            &#60;mm:last&#62;
              &#60;/td&#62;&#60;/tr&#62;
            &#60;/mm:last&#62;
          &#60;/mm:relatednodes&#62;

          &#60;mm:relatednodes type=&#34;people&#34;&#62;
            &#60;mm:first&#62;
              &#60;tr&#62;
                &#60;th colspan=&#34;2&#34;&#62;Authors&#60;/th&#62;
              &#60;/tr&#62;
            &#60;/mm:first&#62;
            &#60;em&#62;&#60;mm:field name=&#34;firstname&#34; /&#62; &#60;mm:field name=&#34;lastname&#34; /&#62;&#60;/em&#62;
            &#60;br /&#62;
            &#60;mm:last&#62;
              &#60;/td&#62;&#60;/tr&#62;
            &#60;/mm:last&#62;
          &#60;/mm:relatednodes&#62;
        &#60;/table&#62;
      &#60;/center&#62;
    &#60;/html&#62;
  &#60;/mm:node&#62;
&#60;/mm:cloud&#62;</programlisting>

    <para>Here we added the &#60;mm:relatednodes&#62; tag to support retrieval
    of our relevant related nodes. Note the usage of the &#60;mm:last&#62; tag
    to close the pending table row and column. Alternative layouts are also
    possible, as this one somewhat obscures the indenting of your HTML
    document and makes it more difficult to debug if you run into errors.</para>

    <para>Remember that with the first page we used the &#60;mm:related&#62;
    tag and not the &#60;mm:relatednodes&#62; tag. [TODO: what&#39;s the
    difference?]</para>

    <para>After you completed this step, check your page in your development
    environment. Your page should look something like below figure if all went
    well.[TODO include screenshot ]</para>

    <graphic fileref="media/newsitem.jpg" />
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Next steps...</title>

    <para>In this tutorial we showed how to build a sample MMBase application.
    Obviously we have only tipped the possibilities that MMBase offers to page
    designers. There are several things you can do from here:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Explore other sample applications shipped with the MMBase
        distro,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Integrate MMBase Tag Library with your favorite page design tool
        like Macromedia DreamWeaver,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Explore the MMBase Tag Library reference guide where all tags
        are documented and supplied with additional samples you can try out.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>A bit more about &#39;providers&#39;, &#39;referrers&#39;,
    &#39;writers&#39; and so on.</title>

    <section>
      <title>Providers/Referrers</title>

      <para>In this tutorial we have seen that tags can cooperate, and work
      together. It is good to know a bit about the abstraction behind this.</para>

      <para>The first tag which we encountered was the &#39;cloud&#39; tag.
      Every tag that wraps functionality needing a cloud must be inside such a
      cloud tag. Those tags are named &#39;cloudreferrers&#39; (see the taglib
      reference for an overview of all cloud referrers).</para>

      <para>The cloud tag itself of course then is a &#39;CloudProvider&#39;.
      That seems a bit silly at first, because perhaps you cannot think of
      something else that could provide a cloud. If you look
      &#39;cloudprovider&#39; up in the reference you see however that there
      is one other cloudprovider, namely the &#39;transaction&#39;-tag. A
      transaction is a special kind of cloud.</para>

      <para>This same scheme can be applied to several other concepts. The
      next one of course is the &#39;node provider&#39; with its counterpart
      the &#39;node referrer&#39;.</para>

      <para>Node referrers are many. The most obvious one is of course the
      field tag. When presenting a field, the field tag of course needs a
      reference to a node variable where the actual field value belongs to.
      Other examples of node referrer tags are the &#39;related&#39; tag and
      the &#39;relatednodes&#39; tag, which list nodes related to the node to
      which they refer as a node referrer.</para>

      <para>These relatednodes tags are of course also node providers. They
      provide nodes, based on the reference to another node.</para>

      <para>For node referrer tags it does not matter which tag exactly is
      the node provider, they only search for the abstract thing which is a
      &#39;node provider&#39;. That&#39;s why a field-tag can be used inside a
      node-tag or a nodelist-tag and so on.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>id&#39;s</title>

      <para>Sometimes it will occur that a node referrer is actually in more
      then one node-provider tag at the same time. For example:
      <programlisting>&#60;mm:node number=&#34;123&#34;&#62;
   &#60;mm:relatednodes type=&#34;urls&#34;&#62;
      &#60;mm:field name=&#34;title&#34; /&#62;
   &#60;/mm:relatednodes&#62;
&#60;/mm:node&#62;</programlisting> Both &#39;node&#39; and
      &#39;relatednodes&#39; are node providers, the field tag is in the body
      of both. So how does it know now of which node provider it should write
      the &#39;title&#39; field?</para>

      <para>The answer is that on default it will use the
      <emphasis>direct</emphasis> parent, so in this case the
      &#39;relatednodes&#39; node provider.</para>

      <para>If however this is not what you want then you need to know the
      following. Every tag, so also every node provider, can have an
      &#39;id&#39; attribute, and every node referrer tag can have the
      &#39;node&#39; attribute. So perhaps you understand already, but the
      example will make it clear if not: <programlisting>&#60;mm:node id=&#34;abc&#34; number=&#34;123&#34;&#62;
  &#60;mm:relatednodes type=&#34;urls&#34;&#62;
      &#60;mm:field node=&#34;abc&#34; name=&#34;title&#34; /&#62;
  &#60;/mm:relatednodes&#62;
&#60;/mm:node&#62;        
</programlisting>You see, now the field searches for a node-provider with id
      &#39;abc&#39;, and that happens to be the mm:node tag. It still has to
      be <emphasis>inside</emphasis> though.</para>

      <para>This mechanism work for every provider/referrer pair. So
      cloud-referrers have a &#39;cloud&#39; attribute, node-referrers have a
      &#39;node&#39; attribute and field-referrers have a &#39;field&#39;
      attribute.</para>

      <para>The &#39;id&#39; attributes of tags are also used for something
      else. Namely to construct &#39;taglib variables&#39; about which we will
      elaborate in the section <xref endterm="taglibvars.title"
      linkend="taglibvars" />.</para>

      <para>But first we will tell a bit about another very basic
      provider/referrer pair, namely the writers and writer referrers.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Writers/Writer referrers</title>

      <para>Another name for &#39;writer&#39; tags could perhaps have been
      &#39;content providers&#39;. These concepts were introduced after the
      observation that there are really two kind of tags. There are tags such
      as the cloud tag and node tag, which do nothing by themselves, they
      merely provide an environment for other tags. On the other hand, there
      are also tags which can actually write something to the page, like the
      field tag, they actually provide content, so to say. (hence the chosen
      name &#39;Writer&#39; and the &#39;content provider&#39; suggestion I
      just did).</para>

      <para>Sometimes we do not want to write the content provided by a writer
      tag to the page, but we want something else. Perhaps we first want to
      check if the content is correct, or perhaps we want to store the content
      in a jsp-variable, or perhaps yet something else.</para>

      <para>So here the concept of writerreferrer tags comes in. It works
      precisely the same as the other referrers we talked about. Writer
      referrers work in the body of &#39;writer&#39; tags. Because of this,
      &#39;Writer&#39; tags behave a bit different if they have a body,
      because only then they start being real &#39;providers&#39;, then they
      simply provide the content to the writer-referrers. But if the
      writer-tag does not have a body, then the most sensible thing is done
      with the content: it is written to the page. This default behavior of
      writer tags can be overriden by their &#39;write&#39; attribute. Using
      this attribute you can perform tricks as &#39;silent&#39; field tags, or
      field tags that write also when they have a body.</para>

      <para>The most simple example of a writer-tag is the write-tag.
      <programlisting>
&#60;mm:write value=&#34;hello world&#34; /&#62;
</programlisting> This will for example just write &#39;hello world&#39; on
      your page. This is a silly thing to do of course, because you could as
      well have used no tag at all for this. In the section about taglib
      variables you will however find out that even the &#39;value&#39;
      attribute of the write-tag can come in useful.</para>

      <para>But the write-tag is also a <emphasis>writer referrer</emphasis>
      tag. Of course, when the write-tag works as a writer-referrer tag, it
      simply takes the content of the &#39;writer&#39; tag it refers to and
      uses that as its own content. <programlisting>
&#60;mm:field name=&#34;title&#34;&#62;
  &#60;mm:write /&#62;
&#60;/mm:field&#62;
</programlisting> So this will simply write the value of the &#39;title&#39;
      field. The field tag itself did not write because it has a body, and the
      write tag inside it referred to it, and wrote it to the page.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Condition tags</title>

      <para>There are a lot of &#39;writer referrer&#39; tags, and most of
      them are also &#39;condition&#39; tags. Condition tags are tags that do
      evaluate their body based on some condition. A condition tag that is
      also writer referrer would naturally do some check on the content
      provided by the writer.</para>

      <para>For example we could write something to the page if the title
      happens to be empty: <programlisting>
&#60;mm:field name=&#34;title&#34;&#62;
  &#60;mm:isempty&#62;
    This news article has no title!
  &#60;/mm:isempty&#62;
  &#60;mm:isnotempty&#62;
     &#60;mm:write /&#62; &#60;!-- write it out then --&#62;
  &#60;/mm:isnotempy&#62;
&#60;/mm:field&#62;
</programlisting></para>

      <para>Condition tags always have a &#39;inverse&#39; attribute to turn
      the condition around. So the following is equivalent:
      <programlisting>
&#60;mm:field name=&#34;title&#34;&#62;
  &#60;mm:isempty&#62;
    This news article has no title!
  &#60;/mm:isempty&#62;
  &#60;mm:isempty inverse=&#34;true&#34;&#62;
     &#60;mm:write /&#62; &#60;!-- write it out then --&#62;
  &#60;/mm:isempy&#62;
&#60;/mm:field&#62;
</programlisting></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>List referrers</title>

      <para>There is also a bunch of condition tags that are not writer
      referrers but list referrers. List tags are naturally those tags that
      evaluate their body zero or more times.</para>

      <para>One of the most used list referrers that is also a condition is
      the &#39;first&#39; tag: <programlisting>
&#60;mm:relatednodes type=&#34;urls&#34;&#62;
  &#60;mm:first&#62;
    &#60;h2&#62;Related urls&#60;/h2&#62;
  &#60;/mm:first&#62;
 .....
&#60;/mm:relatednodes&#62;
</programlisting> Of course, the first tag evaluates its body only if this is
      the first iteration of the list. So, if the list happens to be empty it
      is never executed. In the above example the mm:first tag is used to
      write out a &#39;related urls&#39; header if and only if there are
      actually one or more of such urls. It would be silly to write that
      header if there are no related urls, wouldn&#39;t it?</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="taglibvars">
    <title id="taglibvars.title">Taglib variables</title>

    <para>In the previous section we already mentioned the fact that the
    &#39;id&#39; attribute is also used to create &#39;taglib variables&#39;.
    We will now demonstrate what those are.</para>

    <para>Taglib variables originated from the need to pass around information
    between tags that are not &#39;inside&#39; each other. There is for
    example a tag that creates a relation between two nodes. So, this
    &#39;createrelation&#39; tag would need to refer to two nodes, and not to
    one. It would be silly to demand that the createrelation tag be in two
    nodeproviders. So we came up with this: <programlisting>
&#60;mm:node id=&#34;firstnode&#34; number=&#34;123&#34; /&#62;
&#60;mm:node id=&#34;secondnode&#34; number=&#34;456&#34; /&#62;
&#60;mm:createrelation role=&#34;related&#34; source=&#34;firstnode&#34; destination=&#34;secondnode&#34; /&#62;
</programlisting></para>

    <para>Now, the two nodes under concern are stored somewhere, and the
    createrelation tag uses it. Perhaps it is a good idea to reveal
    immediately where they are stored. They are stored in a &#39;context&#39;.</para>

    <section>
      <title>The context tag</title>

      <para>Every mmbase taglib page implicitly has a context of its own, but
      you can also explicitly define contexts.</para>

      <para>You must know that a context can only contain one instance of a
      variable with a certain name. You will get an error message if you do
      not obey this rule. This means that you run into trouble when you use an
      &#39;id&#39; attribute inside a list, because if the list iterates more
      then once, it will try to put this thing with an id more then once in
      the same context, which it does not allow.</para>

      <para>The solution is to provide the body of a list its own context:
      <programlisting>
&#60;mm:listnodes type=&#34;urls&#34;&#62;
  &#60;mm:context&#62;
     &#60;mm:node id=&#34;thisurl&#34;&#62;
     &#60;/mm:node&#62;
     &#60;mm:createrelation source=&#34;thisurl&#34; destination=&#34;othernode&#34; /&#62; 
     ....
  &#60;/mm:context&#62;
&#60;/mm:listnode&#62;
</programlisting> This is the most common use of the context tag. It can be
      used for other things too, but that is beyond the scope of this
      tutorial.</para>

      <para>Every mmbase tag can write itself to the &#39;context&#39; and
      often it also can get some information from the context. Therefore,
      every mmbase tag is a &#39;context referrer&#39; tag (and because of
      that, has a &#39;context&#39; attribute too)</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The referid attribute</title>

      <para>If a tag was written itself to the &#39;context&#39; by use of its
      &#39;id&#39; attribute, then it must be possible to pick this up later,
      as long - of course - the same context can be referred to. For that, the
      &#39;referid&#39; attribute is used. Lets make it clear with an example.
      <programlisting>
&#60;mm:node id=&#34;my_node&#34; number=&#34;123&#34;&#62;
 ... 
&#60;/mm:node&#62;

...

&#60;mm:node referid=&#34;my_node&#34;&#62;

&#60;/mm:node&#62;
</programlisting> The first node tag has an &#39;id&#39; so, it stores itself
      (or at least its &#39;Node&#39;) in the context. The second node tag
      picks this up with the referid attribute, so there we have node 123
      again.</para>

      <para>Most tags do have a referid attribute, to facilitate this.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>dollar-signs ($)</title>

      <para>So now what happens if we assign an id to a writer tag? Then of
      course the obvious thing will happen, namely that the associated writer
      content is written to the context. This can be picked up later. So now
      you can understand what this will do: <programlisting>
&#60;mm:field id=&#34;title&#34; name=&#34;title&#34; /&#62;
&#60;mm:write referid=&#34;title&#34; /&#62;
</programlisting> Yes, this will write the title field twice.</para>

      <para>It can happen you want to use the value of some writer in the
      attribute of another tag. This would be the natural thing to do:
      <programlisting>
&#60;mm:field id=&#34;type&#34; name=&#34;type&#34; /&#62;
&#60;mm:listnodes type=&#34;&#60;mm:write referid=&#34;type&#34; /&#62;&#34;&#62; &#60;!-- THIS IS NOT POSSIBLE --&#62;
   ..
&#60;/mm:listnodes&#62;
</programlisting> This can however not be done in taglib (of course because
      tags cannot be used inside attributes in XML).</para>

      <para>To solve this, we came up with the dollar-sign notation:
      <programlisting>
&#60;mm:field id=&#34;type&#34; name=&#34;type&#34; /&#62;
&#60;mm:listnodes type=&#34;$type&#34;&#62; 
   ..
&#60;/mm:listnodes&#62;
</programlisting> Dollar signs are often used to indicate that something
      should be interpreted as the name of a variable, e.g. in XML based
      languages like XSL and Ant. Also in script languages like Perl this is
      common practice.</para>

      <para>This will write out the field &#39;title&#39; three times:
      <programlisting>
&#60;mm:field id=&#34;title&#34; name=&#34;title&#34; /&#62;
&#60;mm:write referid=&#34;title&#34; /&#62;
&#60;mm:write value=&#34;$title&#34; /&#62;
</programlisting> Do you understand the difference between the &#39;value&#39;
      and the &#39;referid&#39; attributes?</para>

      <para>Dollar-sign variables can be used in nearly all attributes. It can
      also be combined with other text: <programlisting>
&#60;mm:field id=&#34;title&#34; name=&#34;title&#34; /&#62;
&#60;mm:listnodes type=&#34;news&#34; constraints=&#34;title LIKE &#39;$title&#39;&#34;&#62; 
   ..
&#60;/mm:listnodes&#62;
</programlisting> Sometimes it is needed to use curly brackets to indicate
      where the name of the variable ends: <programlisting>
&#60;mm:field id=&#34;firstname&#34; name=&#34;firstname&#34; /&#62;
&#60;mm:field id=&#34;lastname&#34; name=&#34;lastname&#34; /&#62;
&#60;mm:listnodes type=&#34;news&#34; constraints=&#34;title LIKE &#39;${firstname}${lastname}&#39;&#34;&#62; 
   ..
&#60;/mm:listnodes&#62;
</programlisting></para>

      <para>Also other objects in the context can be used with a dollar-sign
      variable, and usually something sensible happens then. For example the
      dollar-sign value of a node is its number. You can use this for example
      to create an url: <programlisting>
&#60;mm:listnodes id=&#34;article&#34; type=&#34;news&#34;&#62;
    &#60;a href=&#34;&#60;mm:url page=&#34;newsitem.jsp?article=$article&#34; /&#62;&#34;&#62;&#60;mm:field name=&#34;title&#34; /&#62;&#60;/a&#62;
&#60;/mm:listnodes&#62;
</programlisting> The url-tag has more features. Please use the reference
      documentation to learn more about it.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Another way to create taglib variables: import tag</title>

      <para>We have seen the most natural way to put something in the
      &#39;context&#39;, which is using an &#39;id&#39; on some tag. Putting
      explicitly something in the context could therefore be done like this:
      <programlisting>
&#60;mm:write value=&#34;hello world&#34; id=&#34;hello&#34; write=&#34;false&#34; /&#62;
</programlisting></para>

      <para>There is a variant of the write-tag of which the only goal is
      putting things in the context. This is the &#39;import&#39; tag, which
      you have seen before. It is in some way also the inverse of the write
      tag; the write tag is to get things <emphasis>out</emphasis> the context
      (but by chance can also be used to put things in it), but the import tag
      is <emphasis>meant</emphasis> to put things <emphasis>in</emphasis> the
      context. Therefore the import-tag is not a &#39;writer&#39; itself. The
      function of the value attribute of the write tag is taken by the body of
      the import tag. <programlisting>
&#60;mm:import id=&#34;hello&#34;&#62;hello world&#60;/mm:import&#62;
</programlisting></para>

      <para>The body of the import tag is only optional though. Normally the
      import-tag will import from somewhere else in the context. Very often,
      it will be used to &#39;import&#39; a request parameter.
      <programlisting>
&#60;mm:import externid=&#34;greeting&#34; from=&#34;parameters&#34; id=&#34;hello&#34; /&#62;
</programlisting> This will put the value of the request parameter
      &#39;greeting&#39; into the taglib variable &#39;hello&#39;.</para>

      <para>Very often you will be content with a taglib variable with the
      same name, so the &#39;id&#39; attribute is optional if you use the
      externid attribute: <programlisting>
&#60;mm:import externid=&#34;greeting&#34; from=&#34;parameters&#34;/&#62;
</programlisting> This will put the value of the request parameter
      &#39;greeting&#39; into the taglib variable &#39;greeting&#39;.</para>

      <para>These are the basics of the import tag. We refer to the taglib
      reference documentation for a full description.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The parent-writer variable: $_</title>

      <para>In MMBase taglib there is one dollar sign variable with a special
      meaning, which can be very convenient. If you happen to know Perl, you
      will know from where this syntax was borrowed.</para>

      <para>Often it is a bit cumbersome to use an id attribute on some
      writer, because that will often also introduce a context tag (when you
      are in a list), and things get a bit messy. So, you can also use the
      $_-variable which is the equivalent of &#60;mm:write /&#62;, but then
      inside an attribute. <programlisting>
&#60;mm:listnodes type=&#34;news&#34;&#62;
  &#60;mm:field name=&#34;title&#34;&#62;
    &#60;mm:listnodes type=&#34;news&#34; constraints=&#34;title LIKE &#39;$_&#39;&#34;&#62; 
      ..
    &#60;/mm:listnodes&#62;
  &#60;/mm:field&#62;
&#60;/mm:listnodes&#62;
</programlisting> This finds news articles with the same title.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Jsp-variables</title>

    <para>Sometimes the MMBase taglib will not provide enough functionality.
    Since a taglib is always used in a JSP page (this is not so per
    definition, but in practice, this is always so), it would be only logical to
    implement the more complicated things in Java.</para>

    <para>For this to be possible most MMBase tags (I think the exceptions are
    only the &#39;condition&#39; tags) have the &#39;jspvar&#39; attribute.
    With this, a java variable, of which the name is defined by the the value
    of the jspvar attribute, will be instantiated, and can be used in the body
    of the tag. There is for example (in taglib 1.0.1) no taglib way to get
    user information: <programlisting>
&#60;mm:cloud jspvar=&#34;cloud&#34;&#62;
  logged in as &#60;%=  cloud.getUser().getIdentifier() %&#62;
&#60;/mm:cloud&#62;
</programlisting></para>

    <para>Sometimes the type of the variable which must be declared is not
    defined well by the tag. Then a jspvar of type &#39;Object&#39; will be
    declared, which can be inconvenient because then normally you will have to
    cast to the desired type.</para>

    <para>Therefore the tags to which this applies (most noticeably all
    &#39;writer&#39; tags) also feature the &#39;vartype&#39; attribute.
    <programlisting>
&#60;mm:field name=&#34;size&#34; jspvar=&#34;size&#34; vartype=&#34;float&#34;&#62;
  Size of the object: &#60;%= size.floatValue() * 1000 %&#62; millimeters.
&#60;/mm:field&#62;
</programlisting></para>

    <para>The &#39;jspvar&#39; and &#39;vartype&#39; attributes are probably
    the only mmbase taglib attribute which do not accept taglib dollar-sign
    variables. This is fundamentally impossible, because the values of those
    attributes need to be known at compile time.</para>

    <para>The &#39;import&#39; tag is the only tag which does not create the
    jsp-variable in its body (because that is used already for something
    else). The jspvar of an import tag is available <emphasis>after</emphasis>
    the tag. So the import tag provides you a way to create global
    jsp-variables on your page. Global variables are considered bad practice.</para>
  </section>
</article>