<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo >
    <title>Cloud Security Configuration</title>
    <date>2004-06-07</date>
    <edition>$Id: cloud-security.xml,v 1.5 2006-07-09 12:16:46 michiel Exp $</edition>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Henk</firstname>
        <surname>Hangyi</surname>
      </author>
      <author>
        <firstname>Michiel</firstname>
        <surname>Meeuwissen</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <legalnotice>
      <para>This software is OSI Certified Open Source Software. OSI Certified is a certification mark of the Open Source Initiative.</para>
      <para>
        The license (Mozilla version 1.0) can be read at the MMBase site. See 
        <ulink url="http://www.mmbase.org/license" >http://www.mmbase.org/license</ulink>
      </para>
    </legalnotice>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.1</revnumber>
        <date>4 April 2003</date>
        <authorinitials>HH</authorinitials>
      </revision>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.2</revnumber>
        <date>2004-06-07</date>
        <authorinitials>MM</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
  <section id="cloud_security">
    <title>A security implementation that uses the cloud</title>
    <para>
      Cloud security uses the object mmbaseusers to store information used for authorization and
      authentication of users. The two main advantages of this security implementation are that the user
      administration can be carried out by using a web-browser (instead of editing a file on the
      file system) and that the users of your MMBase installation are available as objects in the
      cloud. For instance, it is possible to create groups of users, which are allowed to carry out
      certain tasks. This document gives an overview on how to install and use the cloud security.
    </para>
    <para>
      This is not the only cloud security implementation available. Since MMBase 1.7 there is also a
      'cloud context' security implementation available, which combines the advantages of this cloud
      security with the power of 'context' security. It can be downloaded separately.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="users_ranks_rights">
    <title>Users, ranks and rights</title>
    <para>
      Users are stored in the object 'mmbaseusers'. Users can be added by the user
      'admin' (default password: 'admin2k'). The passwords are stored with an MD5
      encryption, and can only be changed by the user itself, or by the 'admin'.
    </para>
    <para>
      Admin has the rank 'administrator', users that are not logged in have the rank 'anonymous',
      all other users have rank 'basic user'.
    </para>
    <para >For every node in the system the following rules apply:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Every node can be read
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Admin may do everything, except deleting it's own usernode
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Normal users may create new objects of the type's that are not system builders. Objects
          can belong to a user (only that user and the admin can change it) or they may be shared (all logged
          in users can change the node). An object can be given the user [shared] by using the JSP editors.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="installing">
    <title>Installing Cloud Security</title>
    <para>To install Cloud Security you have to:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          add the builder 'mmbaseusers ' to your MMBase installation. After adding the
          builder you have to temporarily turn off security and fill the object 'mmbaseusers ' by the
          admin user. E.g. login admin and password admin2k. See the 'Configuring the security framework'
          on how to switch off security.
        </para>
        <para>
          Another way to add the builder 'mmbaseusers' to your MMBase installation is to load the
          CloudSecurity application. Refer to the documentation on MMBase applications to see how you can load
          applications. After loading the CloudSecurity the user admin / admin2k is automatically added to
          your installation.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          set the authentication and authorization class in the file &lt;config dir&gt;/security/security.xml.
        </para>
        <programlisting>
          &#60;authentication class='org.mmbase.security.implementation.cloud.Authenticate' url='' /&#62;
        </programlisting>
        <programlisting>
          &#60;authorization class='org.mmbase.security.implementation.cloud.Verify' url='' /&#62;
        </programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <note>
      <para>
        It is also possible to only use authentication. When disabling authorization pages can
        still be secured by a login and password. However MMBase does no longer check whether or not an
        MMBase user is allowed to create, change or delete an object. To disable authorization use:
      </para>
      <programlisting>
        &#60;authorization class='org.mmbase.security.NoAuthorization' url='' /&#62;
      </programlisting>
    </note >
  </section >
</article >
    