<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>SearchQuery introduction</title>

  <articleinfo>
    <date>oct 23rd 2002</date>

    <author>
      <firstname>Rob</firstname>

      <surname>van Maris</surname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Finalist IT Group</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
  </articleinfo>

  <sect1>
    <title>background</title>

    <para>The database search queries project addresses the following needs:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>deliver search queries inside MMBase in a uniform and
        device-independent manner</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>provide mechanisms to process these queries in a device-specific
        way that ensures optimal performance</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The plan of action for the project defines three stages:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Create a SearchQuery object to represent all possible search
        queries supported by standard relational databases.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Create an extension mechanism to enable use of additional,
        vendor specific, database functionality.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Integrate of the SearchQuery into existing MMBase code.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>The current state of the project is that stage 1 has been completed.
    This article introduces the resulting SearchQuery design and
    implementation.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>resources</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Sourcecode is available from CVS module speeltuin\dbsq\src.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>JUnit tests sourcecode is available from CVS module
        speeltuin\dbsq\test\src.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>UML diagrams including javadoc are available from the project
        website at mmbase.org.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>package descriptions</title>

    <para></para>

    <sect2>
      <title>org.mmbase.storage.search</title>

      <para>Defines the SearchQuery interface along with all collaborating
      interfaces. </para>

      <para>SearchQuery objects are essentially container objects that hold
      data describing query requests. The storage layer needs to retreive this
      data from the objects in order to process the query. </para>

      <para>The package contains the exact interfaces available to retrieve
      this data from the query objects. </para>

      <para>Note that these interfaces don&#39;t specify how query objects are
      constructed, see next section.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>org.mmbase.storage.search.implementation</title>

      <para>Contains classes implementing the interfaces mentioned above.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</article>