<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>The MMBase Function sets</title>
    <date>2006-04-2006</date>
    <edition>$Id: functionsets.xml,v 1.3 2006-04-11 23:26:26 daniel Exp $</edition>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Daniel</firstname><surname>Ockeloen</surname>
        <affiliation><orgname>MMCoder</orgname></affiliation>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <legalnotice>
      <para>This software is OSI Certified Open Source Software. OSI Certified is a certification mark of the Open Source Initiative.</para>
      <para>The license (Mozilla version 1.0) can be read at the MMBase site. See <ulink
      url="http://www.mmbase.org/license">http://www.mmbase.org/license</ulink></para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>
  <section>
    <title>What are functionsets ?</title>
    <para>
     MMBase function's allow you to add functions/methods to different layers of mmbase and make them available within the MMBase taglib project or bridge. 
	 This way it is possible to add you own functionality in a way thats easy to access. These functions can be added to fields, nodes, builders and clouds
	 each having their own backend implementation but they all share a common way to use them from inside java (bridge) or jsp (taglibs)
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Using functions from the taglibs</title>
      <para>
a simple example of a function on a set (explained later) could be

<programlisting>
example : &lt;mm:function set="util" name="generatePassword" /&gt;
</programlisting>

This calls the funcion generatePassword in the set util, and returns it as a String (the default).

You can have multiple return types that are defined by the way you call them :
<programlisting>
        &lt;mm:function ...      (default String)
        &lt;mm:booleanfunction   (boolean)
        &lt;mm:voidfunction      (no return value)
        &lt;mm:list              (list)
        &lt;mm:nodefunction      (one mmbase node or virtual mmbase node)
        &lt;mm:nodelistfunction  (returns a list of nodes or virtual nodes)
</programlisting>
      </para>
	  <para>
      Functions can have parameters that you can set in several ways the normal way is to ceate a 
	  functioncontainer where you can set the parameters and then call one or more functions.
      <programlisting>
        &lt;mm:functioncontainer&gt;
          &lt;mm:param name="template"&gt;AASSHHM&lt;/mm:param&gt;
           your random new password might be : &lt;mm:function set="util" name="generatePassword" /&gt;
		&lt;/mm:functioncontainer&gt;
	  </programlisting>
      </para>
	  <para>
        Each of the defined parameters will be added to every function within the functioncontainer.
		It is also possible to add parameters using the mmbase referid concept, this is handy when a
		parameter is already loaded into your page using a &lt;mm:import ...
		 <programlisting>
           &lt;mm:import externid="template" /&gt;
        your random new password might be : &lt;mm:function name="getPassword" referid="template" /&gt;
		 </programlisting>
	  </para>
  </section>  
  <section>
    <title>Using functions from the bridge</title>
	<para>
	 TODO
	</para>
   </section>
     <section>
    <title>Defining functions in Builders for functions on builders and nodes</title>
	<para>
	For functions related to one type of nodes you can add functions its builder, they can be executed on either
	one node of on the builder itself. You can define them in 2 ways. One if in the builder.xml and the other is 
	in the java file of the builder itself.
 
	From the example in tests/config/builders/tests/datatypes.xml
     <programlisting>
		&lt;functionlist&gt;
		 &lt;function key="integerFunction" name="aaa"&gt;
            &lt;class&gt;org.mmbase.util.functions.ExampleBean&lt;/class&gt;
		 &lt;/function&gt;
        &lt;/functionlist&gt;
	 </programlisting>
	</para>
	<para>
	Here we defined a function on the datatypes builder with the name 'aaa', When this is called from either the 
	bridge of tags it calles the integerFunction in the org.mmbas.util.functions.ExampleBean.
	<programlisting>
	    public Integer integerFunction() {
                return new Integer(parameter2.intValue() * 3);
        }
	</programlisting>
	</para>
   </section>
     <section>
    <title>Defining functions in Modules</title>
	<para>
	 Its also possible to define functions in MMBase Modules see the MMAdmin module
and its jsp pages in mmbase/mmadmin/.
	</para>
   </section>
   <section>
    <title>Defining functions in Sets</title>
	<para>
     Unlike Module or NodeManagers related functions the set functions are aimed for a global use and can be implemented 
     in any java class or . You can for example define a set 'util' or 'statistics' or even map to external application 'lucien'.
	 Defining sets is done in a 2 xml files. The first defines whats sets you have : 
	 <programlisting>        
	 mmbase config xml : config/functions/functionsets.xml
	 
	    &lt;functionsets&gt;
		  &lt;functionset name="util" file="utils.xml" /&gt;
		 &lt;/functionsets&gt;
	 </programlisting>
	 
	 The set itself (in this case utils.xml) defines the mapping, names, classes and methodes to be called

     <programlisting>
				&lt;functionset&gt;                 
				&lt;description&gt;Some util functions from org.mmbase.util, made accessible through the function-framework&lt;/description&gt;
                 &lt;function name="generatePassword"&gt;
                  &lt;description&gt;Generates a password. Using a template&lt;/description&gt;
                  &lt;type&gt;class&lt;/type&gt;
                  &lt;class&gt;org.mmbase.util.PasswordGenerator&lt;/class&gt;
                  &lt;method&gt;getPassword&lt;/method&gt;
                  &lt;param name="template" type="String"&gt;SSSSSS&lt;/param&gt;
                  &lt;return type="String" /&gt;
                 &lt;/function&gt;
                &lt;/functionset&gt;
	 </programlisting>
	</para>
	<para>
	In this example we only defined one function called generatePassword, its implemented as a class (type) the class 
	file is (org.mmbase.util.PasswordGenerator) and the method that will be called inside that class is getPassword. 
	Next we can define one or more parameters in this case one so the end result will be of this function configuration will be that
	&lt;mm:function set="util" name="getPassword" referid="template" /&gt;  will be mapped to the method String getPassword(String template) 
	inside the class orf.mmbase.util.PasswordGenerator.
	</para>
   </section>
</article>
